<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Ecclesia enucleata: The temple opened: Or, A clear demonstration of the true gospel-church in its nature and consitution, according to the true doctrine and practice of Christ and his apostles. By I.C.</title>
            <author>Chauncy, Isaac, 1632-1712.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 154 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 89 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A32767</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C3750</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R215133</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99827102</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99827102</idno>
            <idno type="VID">31515</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A32767)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 31515)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1863:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Ecclesia enucleata: The temple opened: Or, A clear demonstration of the true gospel-church in its nature and consitution, according to the true doctrine and practice of Christ and his apostles. By I.C.</title>
                  <author>Chauncy, Isaac, 1632-1712.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 160 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by George Larkin at the lower end of Broadstreet, next to London-Wall,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>I. C. = Isaac Chauncy.</note>
                  <note>Includes errata.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Dr. Williams' Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Congregationalism --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church --  Catholicity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:31515:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:31515:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Eccleſia Enucleata:</hi> The Temple Opened: Or, A Clear DEMONSTRATION Of the True <hi>Goſpel-Church</hi> IN ITS Nature and Conſtitution, According to the DOCTRINE and PRACTICE OF <hi>Christ and his Apoſtles.</hi> By <hi>I. C.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>In that day ſeven Women ſhall take hold of one man, ſaying, We will eat our own bread, and wear our own Apparel; only let us be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by thy Name, to take away our Reproach: <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſa. 4.1.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>George Larkin</hi> at the lower End of <hi>Broadſtreet,</hi> next to <hi>London-Wall.</hi> 1684.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:31515:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:31515:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Candid Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>TRue Religion, and the Church of Christ, are Twins; they were conceived and born together, and have grown up together in the World; and I may ſay of them, as of all the Sons of God in particular, <hi>That they are born, not of Blood, nor of the will of the Fleſh, nor of the will of Man, but of God:</hi> John <hi>1.13.</hi> They are only from God, and for God, and his revealed mind and will. In his Word is the great
<pb facs="tcp:31515:3"/> preſcribing Rule of both, and the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Touch-ſtone for an unerring Tryal of the Truth of either. All Preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of humane Wiſdom, Law, and Authority, must here vail their Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net; for if theſe could juſtly claim a binding Power in matters of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, I know no Reaſon why the Great <hi>Turk</hi> hath not as ſtrong Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments for his Religion in all his Dominions, as Chriſtians have any where for theirs; We find (what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Prerogative Secular Powers lay claim to) that they are fully aſſured that Religion never takes place upon mens minds by their Authority only, they muſt pretend to at leaſt a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, as we ſee. The <hi>Turk</hi> muſt have his falſe Prophet <hi>Mahomet,</hi> and his <hi>Mufti;</hi> and the Ten-horn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb facs="tcp:31515:3"/> ſecular Beaſt must have his two-horned Eccleſiaſtical Brute. So the Heathen Kingdoms and Pagan, have always had their Diabolick Prieſts, to influence the Minds, and ſham the Conſciences of Men, by the awe of ſome Divinity, or ſuppoſed Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Authority, into a Reverend e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem of that Religion they deſigned to eſtabliſh, ſuitable to their own car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal deſigns and advantages.</p>
            <p>Since the knowledge of the True God, and the breaking forth of the light of the Goſpel in the Kingdoms of the darkneſs of this world, the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vills Mask hath b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en much removed, he is found to be what he is: His wiles and deceits, whereby he hath ſo long impoſed upon the minds of men, are very much diſcovered, in ſo much
<pb facs="tcp:31515:4"/> that it may be ſaid of him in theſe latter days, that he is <hi>fallen as light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning from heaven,</hi> ſince the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming Angels mentioned <hi>Rev. 14.</hi> have been employed in the Wilderneſs, the three Goſpel flying Angels to bring in that glorious light, and the two Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle Angels that cut down the Harveſt and Vintage, the Thick<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ts and ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding poyſonſome Antichriſtian Trees have been in a great meaſure in many places cut down; yea Reformation hath been carried on to ſuch degrees, that <hi>the Angels have been ſeen, having the ſeven laſt Plagues, and thoſe that have got the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory ovcr the Beaſt, over his Image, and over his Mark, and over the number of his name, ſtanding on the Sea of Glaſs, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb facs="tcp:31515:4"/> the Harps of God, and ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Song of</hi> Moſes <hi>the Servant of God, and the Song of the Lamb,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Yea, the Temple of the Tabernacle of the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony hath been open:</hi> and I doubt not but the ſeven Vial-Angels are coming out of the Temple, though Smoak fill it at preſent, from the <hi>glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God, and his power.</hi> In anſwer to the old enquiry, Where was your Church (<hi>according to Article 19. of the Church of</hi> England) before <hi>Luther?</hi> We ſay, It hath been for above <hi>1200</hi> years in the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; it was before that, ever ſince the Apoſtles tim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, under the <hi>Draconick</hi> Tyranny and Perſecution, till it fell under the Beaſt and Falſe Prophet, in the midſt of Spiritual <hi>Egypt, Sodom</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:31515:5"/> and <hi>Babylon,</hi> out of which it hath been bringing under the conduct of the Angel that was with the Church in the Wilderneſs; by ſeveral removes, steps and degrees of Reformation, ſometimes too wofully luſting and tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning back again. <hi>But God will be a Refiners Fire to all the Sons of</hi> Levi, <hi>he will throughly purge away all the Churches droſs, and take away all her Tin; he will waſh away the Filth of the Daughters of</hi> Zion, <hi>and purge the Blood of</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>from the midſt thereof, by the Spirit of Judgment, and Spirit of Burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</hi> by his trying Providences, and bright ſhining ſearching Light of the Goſpel. In order to the laſt, I have preſumed to caſt in ſome fire from the
<pb facs="tcp:31515:5"/> Altar, have run to and fro a little, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat knowledge may encreaſe, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat many may be purified and made <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hite. Reader, what thou ſeeſt of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arkneſs and ignorance of the Mind <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd Will of Chriſt concerning a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ct of ſo great concern, overlook it of, but lend thy Light alſo, as thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſt received from the Lord Jeſus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hriſt; and remember partiality is to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e laid aſide, and who <hi>ever decrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eth, Chriſt muſt encreaſe.</hi> If thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt no other Argument to reſiſt the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ght offerd, then that the Croſs attends <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ruth, <hi>deny thy ſelf, and take up <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Croſs and Truth,</hi> and follow <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>riſt; this Life &amp; World is but for a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tle while; take heed of b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ggling <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th Conſcience, and ſophiſticating <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Word of God, by ſhifting Gloſſes,
<pb facs="tcp:31515:6"/> to make it ſerve thy own corrupt de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſigns and ends; the Word of God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> pure and conſonant to it ſelf: Chriſt is, and will make it manifeſt and con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſt at laſt, notwithſtanding all oppo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſition, that he is the only Lawgiver his Church; he <hi>ſeeks ſuch Wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhippers as ſhall ſerve him i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Spirit and in Truth:</hi> he hates a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> abhors all Whoriſh Babyloniſh Dr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes of his Worſhip and Ordinance Let Chriſt be found and embrace<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his Church ſought out in the place <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che Wilderneſs where it hath ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nouriſhed: Get true Union to Cbr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Head, becoming a Member of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Myſtical Body, and maintain t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Goſpel-communion of Saints, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> none can harm you.</p>
            <p>The noiſe that ſome men make
<pb facs="tcp:31515:6"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e World of Schiſm and Separation, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> nothing but ſome of Antichriſts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſt, that he throws into the eyes of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſe that he cannot quite blind; for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ere was never any Schiſm in the Myſtical Body of Chriſt, his Veſture <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>as never divided, and there was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>r any true conſtituted Goſpel-Church <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t by Separation; and as for Schiſm, it concerns Viſible Churches, there none ſpoken of in the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent, but ſuch as was found in a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rticular Congregational Church, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ey but ſuperficial Diviſions that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re ſoon healed. He that walks in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e bond of peaceable communion with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> particular Goſpel-Church of Chriſt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll never be hurt by all the Nick-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>mes of Schiſmatick or Dividing-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eparatiſt, that any of the Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers
<pb facs="tcp:31515:7"/> of the Beaſt or his Image, or o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> any carrying the mark or number o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his name, can caſt upon him. It's a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> eaſy thing for men of corrupt minds t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> call what they pleaſe by the name o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Church, and then to ſtigmatize th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Servants of Chriſt in not holding communion with it, by all reproachf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> names of the Devils invention: It <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the greateſt intereſt of every true Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lower of Chriſt, to count the cost of h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Profeſſion, and reſolve that he muſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> through <hi>good report and evil,</hi> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> muſt take a ſhare in the Sufferings <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Chriſt, <hi>who is now crowned wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Glory and Honour,</hi> as all his Fait<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful Members ſhall be, for he hath ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>that where he is, they ſhall b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> alſo:</hi> and doubtleſs there is <hi>a rewa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> for the Righteous, there is a Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:31515:7"/> that Judgeth in the Earth. And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is is the Faith and Patience <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Saints,</hi> and of him who ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eem it honour enough to be found <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e of the leaſt, and am,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy Servant for Chriſts ſake <hi>I. C.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:31515:8"/>
            <head>The Contents of the Chapters contained in this Treatiſe.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHap. 1.</hi> The Deſign of this <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taking. <hi>Page <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 2.</hi> Shewing that a place of Mean<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing is no where taken in the New Testament for a Church of Chriſt <hi>Page 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 3.</hi> Of a National Provincial Church. <hi>Page 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 4.</hi> Of Parochial-Churches. <hi>p. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 5.</hi> Of the Catholick Viſible Church. <hi>Page 6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 6.</hi> Of the moſt uſual acceptation of the word Church in the New Teſtament. <hi>Page 6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 7.</hi> Of a Particular-Church. <hi>P. 7<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 8.</hi> Of the Inferences neceſſary
<pb facs="tcp:31515:8"/> from the foregoing Chapter. <hi>P. 99.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 9.</hi> Of the Bond of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion in the Church. <hi>Page 115.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 10.</hi> of Church-Communion. <hi>Page 136.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 11.</hi> The Concluſion. <hi>Page 155.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:31515:9"/>
            <head>ERRATA</head>
            <p>The Reader is deſired (before he read the Book) to Correct the following Errata's</p>
            <list>
               <item>PAge 24. line 21. after <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> add <hi>at.</hi> line 22. after <hi>Antitype,</hi> add <hi>were.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Page 31. l. 2. read <hi>deſtined to.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Page 37. l. 25. for <hi>jugeled,</hi> read <hi>juggled.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Page 39. l. 11. for <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> read <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>Page 41. l. 3. after <hi>that,</hi> add <hi>though.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Page 50. l. 15. for <hi>munching</hi> read <hi>mouching.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Page 72. l. 21. after <hi>only,</hi> read <hi>of.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Page 78. l. 23. after <hi>Churches,</hi> add <hi>of Judea.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Page 91. l. 14. for <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, read <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</item>
               <item>Page 96. l. 24. for <hi>who they,</hi> read <hi>they who.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Page 100. l. 4. blot out <hi>and.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Page 106. l. 4. blot out <hi>in.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Page 120. l. 14. after <hi>one Body,</hi> add <hi>ſo alſo is Chriſt</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Page 125. l. 23. for <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, read <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</item>
               <item>Page 126. l. 12. for <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, read <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</item>
               <item>Page 141. l. 3. for <hi>parterition,</hi> read <hi>preterition.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Page 142. after <hi>Chriſt,</hi> add <hi>into.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:31515:9"/>
            <head>THE TEMPLE OPENED: OR A Clear Demonſtration OF THE TRUE <hi>GOSPEL-CHURCH.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> The Deſign of this Undertaking.</head>
               <p>AS the true Church of Chriſt is the moſt glorious Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick that ever God crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; in the faſhioning of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hich, his infinite Wiſdom, Power, Goodneſs and Truth did moſt tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendently appear, and wherein he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ath and will magnify all his glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:31515:10"/> Attributes, and his Son Chri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Jeſus the Image of the Fathers Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon, above what he hath done in a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Artifice of the Old Creation: S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> there is no one thing in the wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that Satan and his Inſtruments ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> levyed their Counſels, Power, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Malice more at, ſince the firſt a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pearance of it in the World. B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſeeing he could never prevail by a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the powers of Hell to deſtroy it, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hath managed and carryed on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> deſign principally for the darknin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> clouding, and obſcuring the Glo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of it; and finding the unbelievi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> world began to have their Eyes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pened, and to behold the Glory <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſt and his glorious Body t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Church; He provides a Fob Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and Sham-Church, which he ſet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the world on wondering after. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> when by the light of the Goſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> breaking forth with greater brigh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſs, that ſpiritual <hi>Egyptian</hi> darkne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> which had over-ſpread the <hi>Europe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:31515:10"/> Hemiſphere, began to vaniſh, &amp; that Church was diſcovered to be a Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>agogue of Satan, and a Diabolical Sheat, by her Heatheniſh Idolatries, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>piritual Whoredoms, and whoriſh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ttire; the grand Deceiver betook <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>imſelf to new meaſures, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rived ways and methods for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ounding and darkning the minds of men, that upon the dawning of Goſpel light were ſtudiouſly intent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pon a Reformation. And among other Bombs of Helliſh Mixture that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e flung in and brake among them, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or the diſtracting and dividing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hem in this great Undertaking, this was not the leaſt, To confound <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>heir Language. Fain they would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or the moſt part have Extricated <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hemſelves from the Antichriſtian Labyrinth; and found the way by the Clue of Gods word through that Chymerian Monkiſh darkneſs, in matters of Doctrine, and arrived at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o great a clearneſs and full Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:31515:11"/> of the moſt weighty and neceſſary Points for Life and Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and were ſo abundantly ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in what they believed, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, in Oppoſition to all the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Lyes and Hypocriſies, that Triumphing in their cauſe, <hi>they lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved not their Lives unto Death;</hi> and having weather'd this Cape of good hope even through a Sea of blood, and many a Hurricane of ſmart Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions: They began anon to be becalmed, juſt as they ſhould have Entred the Haven of a full Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation: For falling now under the the Countenance and Favour of Proteſtant Princes, they found not only that eaſe and reſt from Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution was very delightful; and that ſeeing they were ſafe, through the Faith and Patience of their Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors, as to the main points of Salvation, they thought it not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſable to run any further adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in matters, as they thought, of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:31515:11"/> leſſer moment: Seeing the paſſage was alſo Hazardous in reſpect of worldly Pomp and Intereſt; finding that if they went ſo far as the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, plaineſs and ſimplicity of the Goſpel in the worſhip of Chriſt, they muſt lay aſide all that gawdy dreſs of Church Dignities and Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies which the Curtizan of <hi>Rome</hi> had bedaubed it with; and hence, becauſe the <hi>Love of Money is the Root of all Evil,</hi> they came to treat with her for the <hi>Mammon of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteouſneſs;</hi> and it was agreed that the Reformed Religion in all matters of worſhip, ſhould for the moſt part appear in the Romiſh dreſs &amp; attire, &amp; ſhould be accompanyed with the like Profit, Honours &amp; Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, that ſo the honeſt woman might not be diſtinguiſhed from the whore by the Dreſs, and this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd in the ſtreet. And now I ſay, behold Satans great Subtilty; when he hath obtained thus much, that
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:31515:12"/> theſe two Ladies walk up and down in one faſhion, he calls them both by one Name; ſo that now men begin to queſtion their difference, and ſuſpect they are related to each other, as <hi>Aholah</hi> and <hi>Aholibah;</hi> and many finding the Reformed Church ſo like unto the <hi>Romiſh,</hi> they doubt whether there be any ſuch thing as a true Church of Chriſt on Earth; and ſeeing ſo many women play the whore, do queſtion whether there is any honeſt woman living: But <hi>many run to and fro, and knowledge increaſing,</hi> ſome tell us, and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently affirm, they have found this Church or Chriſt; and that all this while it hath been in the Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Wilderneſs: And others en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring into it, ſay, Surely it is ſo; there is much of the Sweetneſs of Chriſts Love, and conſolations of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: But yet there are many things dark and obſcure, and ſo will be, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til ſuch time as this <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> cheat
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:31515:12"/> be perfectly diſcovered to the minds of men, and that whole fabrick de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed.</p>
               <p>Among all the Miſts and Foggs that this Miſtreſs of Sorceries hath raiſed to loſe the true Spouſe of Chriſt in it, there's not many hath been greater then the confuſion of Languages, and eſpecially about the word <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Schiſm,</hi> that all Enquirers ſpake of the Church, but no two meant the ſame thing; men generally agreed there <hi>was a Church, and a true one;</hi> (excluding <hi>Rome</hi>) but could not tell what a kind of thing it ſhould be; and great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions have been and are to this day about it. Some ſay, Here is the Church; and others, that it is there; and every one cries up his Church, and calls others Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks; and they that get power into their hands, deal with others as ſuch.</p>
               <p>Now it would be worth our while to ſearch after many (who
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:31515:13"/> have found) for confirmation of thoſe that will be perſwaded of the Truth, and to examine every Church that pretends to that Name, by the Teſt of the Goſpel, that we may be fully reſolved what metal each is made of. I know all Chriſtians of what mould or ſize whatever, do pretend to lay no <hi>other Foundation then Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> and its well if it were true of all profeſſing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Proteſtants; for that <hi>Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation is a Rock,</hi> and they are ſo far wiſe that lay Chriſt as ſuch in their writings and doctrine; but yet that will not bear an ill Superſtructure: as a good one will not long ſtand on a bad foundation, ſo a good foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation will not long bear up an ill Superſtructure, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.11, 12. <hi>Other Foundation can no man lay then that is laid, which is Jeſus Christ. Now if any man build upon this Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, Gold, Silver, Precious-ſtones, Wood, Hay, Stubble; Every mans
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:31515:13"/> work ſhall be manifeſt, for the day ſhall declare it, becauſe it ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed by fire, and the fire ſhall try every mans work of what ſort it is,</hi> verſe 14. <hi>If any mans work abide which he hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uilt thereupon, he ſhall receive a reward,</hi> verſe 15. <hi>If any mans work ſhall be burnt, he ſhall ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer loſs, but he himſelf ſhall be ſaved,</hi> [provided he lay a good foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on] <hi>yet ſo as by fire;</hi> I doubt not but many good mens and Miniſters Church-works will be burnt, and they will ſuffer loſs; it will be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt one day to be the great ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh of the <hi>Reformation,</hi> that ſo many good men that have Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Chriſt clearly as to his Sonſhip, Natures, Offices, Merits and Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction for Juſtification and Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cation, have from intereſt, preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice or ignorance, extreamly fum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in moſt of the concerns of his Goſpel-Church. I have much ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired to hear ſome mens Pulpit-zeal
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:31515:14"/> againſt ſin in general, and for the advancement of holineſs, even to a juſtifying condition; and when we come to enquire of the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar caſes for the practice of it in Goſpel and revealed Religion, in du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties toward God, they can tell you of nothing but moral natural Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and reduce all the Service of God under the Goſpel thereto; ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they have no other Rule to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect us there, but ſuch as this, <hi>Let every ſoul be ſubject to the Higher Powers, Rom.</hi> 13.1. So as for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed Religion under the Goſpel, our judgments and practice muſt be wholly regulated by, and reſolved into the wills, laws and commands of men.</p>
               <p>But to come to the matter we in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, ſeeing the word <hi>Church</hi> is cloathed with ſo great ambiguity, and ſo much duſt raiſed about it, to the perplexing of mens minds and Conſciences, we ſhall principally
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:31515:14"/> fix our Enquiries for the true ſence and notion of the word upon the tenure of the Goſpel, and the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Spirit of God there; knowing that it is That hath the greateſt power upon the Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of men, when it comes with e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence and demonſtration, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince us of Truth; and whereas fire and ſword, yea mens great words and looks, may terrify fleſh and blood: yea Pulpit Thunder-Claps, diſcharged on the behalf of Error and Nonſenſe, do keep many weak judgments and conſciences in bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage and thraldom, afrighting them from an impartial ſearch for truth, by hard names, equivocating words, paſſionate and zealous ways of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion; yet a Conſcience truly enlightened by Divine Teſtimony is very little concern'd at ſuch things, any more than to pity ſuch paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Soul-confounding blind guides, and much more their poor deluded enſlaved Followers.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:31515:15"/>
               <p>I ſhall handle this word <hi>Church</hi> two ways, for our more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct underſtanding its true Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel meaning.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Shew in what ſence it is not uſually taken.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In what ſence it is<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:31515:15"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Shewing that a place of Meeting is no where taken in the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament for a Church of Chriſt.</head>
               <p>IT's neceſſary to intimate concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in General, that tho' it be taken for a Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation or Aſſembly of people, yet it's not alwayes limited to a religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous one, but is uſed by Claſſick Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, for any Aſſembly; prophane, civil or religious; and ſo it's uſed expreſly, <hi>Acts</hi> 19. for a prophane and <hi>tumultuous aſſembly,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and for a <hi>civil lawful Court or Aſſembly, ver.</hi> 39. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> the firſt of which was diſmiſſed <hi>ver.</hi> 40. But in the proper and uſual ſence of the Spirit of God in the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, it's every where, except in the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:31515:16"/> place above mentioned, taken for a Church of Chriſt in one ſence or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother; and therefore that we may be aſſured in what ſences it is under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, it's neceſſary to winnow the Chaff from the Wheat, and ſet aſide ſuch things as through the miſtakes of men, error, cuſtom and carnal intereſt, are uſually called ſo, and impoſed as ſuch upon erring or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinking judgments, when Chriſt and his Goſpel never called them ſo.</p>
               <p>Firſt there is nothing more fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent among us, then to call a <hi>place of meeting for Publick-Worſhip, a Church:</hi> I affirm there is no juſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of underſtanding it ſo in the New Teſtament, no not in a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonymy-ſence: though Learned Mr. <hi>Joſeph Mede</hi> takes a great deal of pains to prove that the word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> [1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.22. <hi>Have ye not hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to eat and drink in, but deſpiſe you the Church of God?</hi>] is there to be underſtood for the material place
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:31515:16"/> of ordinary aſſembling together for the Worſhip of God, and ſaith, that their Oratories where they frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly met, were called Churches; and yet in the begining of his diſcourſe he ſaith, <hi>It is taken for granted in a manner by the moſt of our Reformed Writers, and affirmed by ſome of the other ſide, that in the Apoſtles times, and ages next after them; (whilſt the Church lived under Pagan and Perſecuting Emperours) Chriſtians had no Oratories or places ſet apart for Divine Worſhip; but that they aſſembled here and there promiſcuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and uncertainly, as they pleaſed, or the occaſion ſerved, in places of common uſe, and not otherwiſe;</hi> which thing undoubtedly is juſtly enough (and upon grounds more evident) belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, then any reaſons brought to prove the contrary by that worthy perſon, wherein he acknowledgeth himſelf almoſt ſingular in this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking, and lays his firſt and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:31515:17"/> greateſt ſtreſs on that expreſſion, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.22. <hi>Here</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>I take the word</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>or Church, to note not the Aſſembly, but the place appointed for ſacred duties, and that from the oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition thereof to</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>their own hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; theſe are places proper for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and ordinary repaſt, and not the Church or houſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of God.</hi> This is the only argument which he brings, beſides ſome obſcure paſſages of ſome Fathers whoſe opinions will not ſway here, but as in other things, ſo far as we ſee them conſonant to the truth, manifeſt in Scriptures, compared together; and it ſeems ſtrange that the word ſhould have a tropical meaning in this place, and every where elſe a proper one: and beſides, the reaſon from the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition will not hold, eſpecially if we conſider what Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtands thoſe Oratories or Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of theirs to be. <hi>It is not to be i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magined that in the firſt three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:31515:17"/> years before</hi> Conſtantines <hi>time, that they were ſuch goodly and stately ſtructures as the Church had after the Empire became Christian — At the firſt ſome capable and convenient Room within the walls or dwelling of ſome pious Diſciple, dedicated by the religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous bounty of the owner, to the uſe of the Church, and that uſually an</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>upper room, or Caenaculum;</hi> It's very probable that all the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples houſes were at the ſervice of the Churches; but that any one houſe (or room in a houſe) was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated ſo to that religious uſe, as to be ſeparated for it from common uſes when the <hi>Church</hi> met not, is not probable at all: for in times and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Perſecution, if Churches meet in any certain houſe or place, though in a private houſe, they ſhall be ſure to be interrupted and broken in upon by Perſecuting Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers and Informers. The only place met in for ſome time conſiderable,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:31515:18"/> that we read of, was <hi>Pauls</hi> own hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red houſe at <hi>Rome;</hi> but we find not that it was conſecrated or called a Church. I am ſure conſecrated Barns, Garrets, Cellars, or Dining Rooms, would be eſteemed by our devout Eccleſiaſticks a great Abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination.</p>
               <p>But how will the Oppoſition hold, if the Room called the Church, was in the ſame houſe they eat and drank ordinarily in? He ſhould have rather ſaid, Have ye not Kitchens or Parlours of common uſe to eat and drink in, but you muſt deſpiſe or put a Prophanation on the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret, which is the Church of God? Beſides, if that Addition had not been made to the Church, I ſhould much rather have enclined to Mr. <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>des</hi> ſence, if he had ſaid only, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe ye the Church? But I take it, that it would be a very audacious and highly abuſive Expreſſion, to ſay, T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at a Meeting-houſe is a
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:31515:18"/> 
                  <hi>Church of God, or a Church of Chriſt:</hi> And why is not the Oppoſition as full thus? <hi>Have you not houſes to eat and drink in, or Families</hi> [for ſo the word is uſed] <hi>But you muſt do it in the Church-Aſſemblies?</hi> for they made their Love-feaſts in their Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies. It is evident enough that the Apoſtle takes <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> for the Aſſembling of the Church together, as <hi>verſ.</hi> 18. where its uſed: when you meet together in Aſſembly, (<hi>i. e.</hi> when you are Congregated toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) I hear that there have been Diviſions (or Schiſms) among you, and thoſe he means had the Diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, who were the Church, for the Goſpel aſcribes culpable Schiſmes no where, but to Body Politicks, or Aſſemblies, not to Houſes. But if we grant Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> all that he ſo induſtriouſly labours to ſqueeze out of the Text, only to favour the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative Holineſs of ſuch places; its not to be ſuppoſed that he intended
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:31515:19"/> that they were real and proper Churches, but only Metonymical Churches, by a Trope, and impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly ſo named; no otherwiſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowable names; putting the <hi>Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nens pro contento,</hi> to diſtinguiſh places allotted to convenient aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling in Religious Worſhip, from Town-halls, and other houſes of meeting together for publick con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns, or more private Society and Converſation. And ſo we loſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing by it, if ſuch a place be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led improperly a Church, its not the Church of Chriſt intended in the Goſpel which Chriſt purchaſed with his blood; nor built of living ſtones, nor ſuch as Chriſt is the Head of; nor ſuch as <hi>Paul</hi> wrote his Epiſtles too; nor the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> which he exhorts, rebukes, and commends in the Epiſtles that he wrote: And therefore we may with the greateſt aſſurance con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that no place where Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:31515:19"/> Aſſemblies frequently uſe to be, is a Church of Chriſt; or may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly be ſo called.</p>
               <p>They that plead the Expreſſion in the <hi>Epheſian Town-Clerks,</hi> Speech, [Act. 19.37. <hi>Ye have brought hither theſe which are neither Robbers of Churches.</hi>] Shew their little skill in the Original Text, the word is, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Robbers of Temples, ſuch as were dedicated to the Heathen Gods and Godeſſes, to which they aſcribed not only Relative, but inherent Holineſs; and therefore adapted that name to them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:31515:20"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Of a National and Provincial CHURCH.</head>
               <p>CHriſt never inſtituted any ſuch Church under the Goſpel Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration, as a National and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincial, or Dioceſan: there is as much for one as for the other, there's no ſeeming pretence can be made for any of them, from any Goſpel Expreſſion: when I ſay this, I mean not a Church in a Nation, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince or Dioceſs, nor all the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Churches in ſuch place, col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectively and co-ordinately conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered. But I mean in the uſual ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation of ſuch Churches in our day, as of <hi>France,</hi> of <hi>Spain,</hi> of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark, &amp;c.</hi> and in the ſence that a
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:31515:20"/> National Church was taken in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Old Teſtament, <hi>viz.</hi> an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganized National, Provincial, or Dioceſan Church, that have Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers or Members ſuited to their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Natures and Conſtitution, as Paſtors, and other Officers, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſing National, Provincial, or Dioceſan Juriſdiction in Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Courts, or elſewhere; and Members, <hi>quatenus</hi> Natives of ſuch places, being therefore ſaid to be born within the Pale of the Church, or by vertue of ſuch Nativity have immediate right to baptiſm, and made ſo.</p>
               <p>I ſay, that that word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> no where ſignifies ſuch a Church in the New Teſtament, except when there is mention made of the Church of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and the word is but once uſed in Application to them, Act. 7.38. <hi>This was he who was in the Church in the Wilderneſs;</hi> this we own was a National
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:31515:21"/> Church: but elſewhere in the New Teſtament, I know not of one place where <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> can with any fair pretence be underſtood of a National Church.</p>
               <p>Beſides it may be argued from undeniable reaſons, that Chriſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted or intended not ſuch a Church for the days of the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>If it be duely weighed, that Chriſt by his Death put a full Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod to the whole <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Cecono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, Nationality being the form of its conſtitution; Having Officers, Members, Aſſemblies and Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſuited to its Nature. The <hi>Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronick</hi> Prieſthood was National, a Type of Chriſts Prieſthood, relating to his univerſal Church; this Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood with all the appertaining Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices, Ordinances, Ceremonies, the Manifeſtation of the Antitype aboliſhed; yea that kind of Church Memberſhip was utterly aboliſhed, (<hi>viz.</hi> that none could be a Member
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:31515:21"/> of that Church but a <hi>Jew</hi> born, or one Proſelyted to that Nation) it being the only Nation in the Earth that God had choſen, with Exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of all other, till Chriſt came and brake down the <hi>Partition-Wall</hi> between <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Gentile,</hi> after which no man was any longer to be rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned ever the more a Church-mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, becauſe he was a Native of this or that Country; <hi>Col.</hi> 3.11 But in the conforming to Chriſts likeneſs, <hi>There is neither Greek nor Jew, Circumciſion nor <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncircumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, Barbarian, Scythian, Bond or Free; but Chriſt is all in all:</hi> and therefore of whatever Nation a man be of, if he believe on the Lord Jeſus Chriſt he ſhall be ſaved, and becomes a capable Member of the viſible Church; and where-ever he is born, without Faith in Chriſt, he cannot be ſaved; neither is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a viſible credible Profeſſion thereof, capable of communion
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:31515:22"/> with the Viſible Church in all Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances.</p>
               <p>Moreover Chriſt Jeſus aboliſhed all the National Church Aſſemblies and Ordinances; for the <hi>Jews</hi> as they were one Organized Church, ſo they were to be but one Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; (which is not known now of any one Nation) aſſembling toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the Worſhip of God in one place, where their Ark of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant was, and therefore the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle of Publick Worſhip was called the Tabernacle of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation; <hi>where all the Males were required to appear before the Lord thrice a year,</hi> Exod. 14.23, 24. whereby they ſhewed themſelves aſſembled and a Congregated Nation, all in actual communion in the ſame Church-Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and in one place, all which was duly to be obſerved during the time of the Tabernacle and ſtanding of the Temple; and though they
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:31515:22"/> corruptly retained their high places for offering ſome Sacrifices during moſt of that time, till the full Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation in <hi>Hezekiahs</hi> and <hi>Joſiahs</hi> days; yet the Lord ſtill charged it on them as their great ſin, and wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed againſt it by his Meſſengers the Prophets as ſuch. And though they had their ſeveral Synagogues, they were but for reading of the Law, not for Sacrifice or Burnt-of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering, which were National Servi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and were to be diſpenſed only at the Tabernacle of the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, or at the Temple; yea, all Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices &amp; Expiations, Purifications, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> appertaining to particular Levi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Uncleanneſſes, or moral tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions, were there to be perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med.</p>
               <p>Now our Lord Jeſus Chriſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver erected ſuch a Goſpel-worſhip after this was aboliſhed, either for matter or form; neither a Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Congregation, nor a National
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:31515:23"/> Paſtor, as <hi>Aaron;</hi> nor Ordinances adapted to a National communion, as the Sacrifices of old were, he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver intended in this way or manner to edify his Goſpel-Church.</p>
               <p>Beſides, As Chriſt eſtabliſhed the Church of the Goſpel, it was not capable of ſuch a conſtitution, ſuch being impoſſible to be ſuſtained without the countenance, if not the compulſive power of civil pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; and we ſee that <hi>de facto</hi> it came into the ruines, when ever in the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Nation, Wicked Kings ſwayed the Scepter; we well enough are aſſured that our Saviour and his Apoſtles formed the Goſpel-Churches every where under Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Princes and Governours, who were for the moſt part ſevere Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors of them, witneſs their Sufferings in the Apoſtles days, and during the Chriſtians bloody Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions, till <hi>Constantines</hi> time, for 300 years, at which time of proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:31515:23"/> this National or then rather Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincial corrupt grandeur of Church-conſtitution began to enter, procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding from the corrupted minds of Church Officers, aſpiring to the accumulation of riches &amp; honours. Soon after they fell under the <hi>Arrian</hi> Hereſy, under which the ſame Church pomp continued, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded to grow with much Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, and confuſion, and diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in the world; with the dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly increaſe of all manner of corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in doctrine and worſhip, even to the introduction of Heatheniſh Abominations in the worſhip of God, till the mortal wound was given to one of the ſeven heads of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Empire, and was healed by the eighth, which was the falſe Prophet the Grand Church Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter; under which the great Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy hath ſo manifeſtly prevailed, and during whoſe Uſurpation the true Church of Chriſt hath been in
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:31515:24"/> the Wilderneſs, and the Witneſſes Propheſying in Sackcloth. So that our Bleſſed Lord and Saviour ſeeing the preſent ſtate of his lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Flock when he aſcended, and foreſeeing their future Suffering State for ſo many Ages to come, under <hi>Rome Heathen,</hi> and after pretendedly Chriſtian, conſtituted ſuch a frame of Goſpel churches, that were capable of being Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Polities under Heathen and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian Princes and Governours, and fitted Officers and Ordinances for their communion and edification ſuited to ſuch a ſtate; which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution was to laſt by his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to the end of the world, not alterable to another kind by the will of man in the enſuing proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous eſtate that the Church might he bleſſed withal in after ages; (which hath been very rare hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to) nor much to be prejudiced as to its truly intended Oeconomy by
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:31515:24"/> the afflictions and ſufferings that it was deſtined by faith and patience to encounter withal.</p>
               <p>Hence it will appear, there being a Politick Impoſſibility, that the Church-conſtitution Eſtabliſhed by Chriſt and his Apoſtles, could be National, becauſe of the Power of the Dragon raging ſo much againſt it in Governours, and Rulers of the Earth; during the time of the firſt Ages of it, and afterward for the moſt part, by reaſon of the Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and Uſurpation of the falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet. And when that any time in any Nations, it was favoured with the countenance of Chriſtian Kings and Princes, had it been National, it muſt have been ſubject to all the Alterations, Additions, and Dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutions in Form and Worſhip, which the corrupt and changeable minds of men in Power would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent and impoſe, eſpecially upon change of Governours and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:31515:25"/> though Chriſtian, yet divers in their Tempers, Underſtandings, and Opinions concerning Gods true Worſhip, as alſo, in their Intereſts and carriages towards the Church, that it would be the moſt difficult thing in the World to have known the manner <hi>and Faſhion of Chriſts houſe.</hi> Wherefore (the Apoſtle ſaith, Heb. 3.1.) <hi>Holy Brethren, Partakers of the Heavenly calling, Conſider the Apoſtle and High Prieſt of our Profeſſion, Chriſt Jeſus;</hi> verſ. 2. <hi>Who was faithful to him that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed him, as alſo Moſes was faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in all his houſe, [i. e.</hi> in all things appertaining to the Worſhip of God in his Church,] verſ. 3. <hi>For this man was counted worthy of more Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry then Moſes, in as much as he who builded the houſe, hath more Honour then the houſe;</hi> verſ. 5. <hi>Moſes veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly was faithful in all his houſe as a Servant, for a Teſtimony of thoſe things that were to be ſpoken after;</hi>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:31515:25"/> verſ. 6. <hi>But Christ as a Son over his own houſe, [in which he is a chief corner ſtone, and hath a greater Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety then</hi> Moſes <hi>had upon all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects] whoſe houſe are we, &amp;c.</hi> i. e. The faithful in the times of the Goſpel are the houſe and Church of Chriſt, and not this or that Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or Province, lying continually at the mercy and diſpoſitions of the wills of Princes, guided by carnal intereſts, and acted by corrupt minds, to the modelling of it, by mutable Laws, as they ſhall corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpond moſt with their State-deſigns and purpoſes, which had been a great ground to have ſuſpected the faithfulneſs of Chriſt, if he had left his Church under ſuch a <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi>-like form and conſtitution, as to be lyable to all the models, chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and alterations of future ages, that the powers of the world would form them into; under a pretence of profeſſion of Chriſtianity, when
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:31515:26"/> as very few of them, if they were duely weighed in the ballance of the Sanctuary, will prove to be much more then almoſt Chriſtians.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, The purpoſe and deſign of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt by his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnation, Sufferings, Miracles wrought, and Doctrine Preached by himſelf and Apoſtles, was the gathering both Jews and Gentiles Elect into one Body, his Church, where-ever ſcattered or diſperſed, not reſpecting one Nation or peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple more then another, any further then in reſpect of the Elect Ones among them, nor deſigning any Kingdom as yet in this world with External Pomp and Grandeur, but rather a continuation of a Suffering State, with very little intermiſſion, under the powers of the Earth, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſing the rage and cruelty of the Dragon againſt the Church; and afterward the Tyranny and Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation of the <hi>Seven Headed Romiſh
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:31515:26"/> Beast and Falſe Prophet;</hi> neither deſigned he the <hi>calling of many wife men after the Fleſh, not many migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, not many noble,</hi> 1 Cor. 1.26. o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe then which he would cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly have done, had he deſigned National &amp; Provincial Churches; he would have ſaid, I deſign a Church that may top, at leaſt give check to earthly Kings &amp; Princes; I will turn their heart &amp; make them mine, both they, and their Subjects: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I will call <hi>many wiſe men after the Fleſh, many mighty and many noble perſons,</hi> who ſhall rule, manage, and defend my Church, which may be in after-ages, but we ſee it quite contrary yet. Ver. 27. <hi>God hath cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen the fooliſh things of this world, to confound the wiſe; and God hath choſen the weak things of this world to confound the things that are migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and baſe things of this world, and things that are deſpiſ'd,</hi> to cary on <hi>his</hi> ſpiritual rule. Believe it this matter
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:31515:27"/> cannot conſtitute a National Church it muſt be another ſort of men. Whatever men therefore may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently aſſert, and however they make a boaſt, and vaunt themſelves of National Churches, Officers, Members, yea, and National Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction and Judicature, exerted in Spiritual Courts, ſo called, none of which were of Chriſt's Appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Inſtitution; but were the meer products of Humane Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licies, and meer <hi>Antichristian Shams</hi> put upon the poor carnal blind world, whereby that Wicked One endeavours to carry away the eyes and hearts of the children of men from the true, plain and Spiritual Spouſe of Chriſt; and go a whoring after Harlots that are agreeable to the faſhions of this world, in Pride, Pomp, Pleaſures, Covetouſneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And I ſay, though ſuch Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Powers, as alſo <hi>Civil,</hi> may deal very hardly upon this account
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:31515:27"/> with the true <hi>Followers of the Lamb,</hi> and <hi>Deluding Pulpiteers</hi> may terrify and fright ſome more weak and leſs <hi>grounded Christians,</hi> with ambiguous words, miſ-interpretation and falſe application of the Scriptures of Truth; <hi>calling light darkneſs, and darkneſs light;</hi> calling what they pleaſe, Church, Charity, Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, Uniformity, Schiſm, Separati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Rebellion, Diſobedience to Laws, Governments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Yet through the <hi>mercy of the moſt High,</hi> there are ſome that have <hi>bought the Truth</hi> in theſe latter dayes of light at dear rates of Sufferings, with expence of Eſtates, Liberties and Lives under the Antichriſtian Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny, and taſted ſo much of the ſweetneſs and excellency of it, that <hi>they</hi> will not ſell it, ſo as to part with it for worldly intereſt, or be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighted from it, by the open mouths of Roaring Lyons, nor jugaled out of it by the Sham-Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:31515:28"/> of the ſlie Foxes that ſpoil the Vines.</p>
               <p>We have nothing to ſay to ſuch men, but as <hi>Hannah</hi> ſpake, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.3. <hi>Talk no more ſo proudly, let not arrogancy come out of your mouth, for the Lord is a God of Knowledge, and by him Actions are weighed.</hi> And as for ſome good old <hi>Ely</hi>'s who are too much blinded with preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, paſſion and intereſt, keep a great ſputter againſt Schiſm, Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration from the Church, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and do not ſeldom grieve the hearts of Chriſts Members, by their unwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable doctrines and practices in the great concerns of Gods Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and but gently rebuke <hi>Hophni</hi> and <hi>Phineas,</hi> we are very well aſſured, that however they may have laid a a good foundation in ſome people, yet their ſuperſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture is but hay and rubbiſh, which ſhall certainly be burnt, <hi>and the day ſhall make it manifeſt</hi> what it is.</p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:31515:28"/>
               <p>The only Plea that is made for a National Church, that is worth our Obſervation, is from the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſies of Old, of <hi>calling in the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Sprinkling many Nations, &amp;c.</hi> Iſa. 5.26. chap. 52.15. chap. 45.1.</p>
               <p>This Argument hath little in it to prove a Goſpel National Church, for theſe and ſuch like Propheſies, reſer to the calling of the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles;</hi> the word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is indifferent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rendred <hi>Gentiles</hi> and Nations, and it intends no more then the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of the elect <hi>Gentiles,</hi> ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered up and down in all Nations; and if it be to be underſtood of ſome whole Nations becoming Chriſtian, it argues nothing of the neceſſity that the Nation ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come one Church Organized; but that the Goſpel-Profeſſion of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, and the Goſpel-churches, ſhould overſpread the moſt of a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or prevail upon the ruling part of it (though very ſeldom)
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:31515:29"/> to be brought in Subjection to the Crown, Scepter, and Laws of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt; Erected in vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Churches, planted there.</p>
               <p>And its no hinderance, but that chriſtian and religious Magiſtrates have Scope enough to Exert that power which Chriſt hath entruſted them withal, as ſuch, for his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Intereſt, in making and Executing Laws for Reſtraint of Sin, and Encouragement of Vertue, in all matters touching Natural Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; as likewiſe, in taking care for the effectual Propagation, as much as may be, in a due way and manner, of the Revealed Religion, and by being Nurſing Fathers to the Churches, countenancing and encouraging them in all ſtrict Obſervation of the commands of Chriſt, and Exemplary converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, both as Churches and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Chriſtians, defending them from the the Rage, Malice, and
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:31515:29"/> Perſecution of the Profeſſed Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>But know that a chriſtian Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate rightly informed in his Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty as Chriſtian and Magiſtrate, hath a Heart and Opportunity to uſe both thoſe capacities for the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Intereſt of Chriſt, more then a Heathen Magiſtrate; yet his being a Chriſtian, adds not unto his Authority as Magiſtrate, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth Chriſtianity <hi>de jure,</hi> extend his Legiſlative Power further then it was before: And therefore if the Magiſtrate, as ſuch, hath a Legiſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Power in matters of Religion, then all have, and Heathen as well as Chriſtian; and that power which the Magiſtrate hath <hi>Jure divino,</hi> we are bound <hi>Jure divino</hi> to obey. <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go</hi> required to be of that Religion the Magiſtrate by Law impoſeth of one kind or another. This is an undeniable conſequence.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:31515:30"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Of Parochial Churches.</head>
               <p>THere is no ſuch things as a <hi>Parochial Church</hi> deducible from Rules of the Goſpel, neither can it be ſhewed that the word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in the New Teſtament doth any where import ſuch a meaning from any Application of it there made by the Spirit of God. What Pleas able and learned men have made for ſuch Churches, you muſt give us leave to reject, unleſs they carry Scripture light and demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration along with them, without which our minds and conſciences cannot be bound to Faith and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion.</p>
               <p>A <hi>Parochial Church</hi> we take in the moſt common and candid Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:31515:30"/> (without binding our ſelves to the Term Parochial, or Pariſh, that being but of latter times) That all Perſons cohabiting within ſuch Bounds, Limitations, or Diviſions of Ground, becoming a Pariſh, Townſhip, Village, or go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing under any other Denomination by the Cuſtoms or Laws of the Land where they are<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I ſay ſuch Diviſions and Limitations of ground, doth not ſet out the bounds of a Goſpel-Church, but that it may extend further then ſuch Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks, or be of leſſer Extent, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Number or Situation of the Profeſſing Believers in thoſe parts, for conveniency of their aſſembling together, and Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion for mutual Edification; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is it neceſſary that all co-inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants within ſuch limits ſhould be Members of one and the ſame Congregation; yea that all ſhould be reputed fit matter for any, ſeeing
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:31515:31"/> nothing is more evident and every where experiencd, than that there is the greateſt mixture of all ſorts of men in ſuch limits and neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoods; common and natural Juſtice allowing every one that habitation that he can claim a civil right and title to, let him be good or bad; its not Religion that makes men members of this or that Pariſh, or Irreligion that excludes them. Now if co-habitation in ſuch a Precinct makes a man a member of the Church of Chriſt there, (if there be any) it is either becauſe it makes him neceſſarily ſo, or gives him a due claim: if the firſt, he muſt be one whether he be willing or no, and ſo long as he dwells in thoſe limits, they can enforce him to be ſo; and then the Church muſt be ſuppoſed to have a compulſive Power, not only internal by moral Perſwaſions, but a Spiritual, as to the exerciſe of Cenſures towards
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:31515:31"/> them that are without, which is Nonſence and ridiculous; yea an external compulſive power on mens Perſons and Actions to be exerted by themſelves, or ſome by and under them, in order to make men Church-members; and this is ſo great a contradiction not only to the Tenure of the Goſpel, yea wholly without any Preſident un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the old or new Teſtament-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions, and to the moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Underſtanding of the Nature of Religion, that to aſſert it is moſt groſly abſurd to any underſtanding Chriſtian Ear, and therefore not worth inſiſting upon. Or it gives him a right and claim; but co-ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation gives not a man a right and claim; <hi>Ergo:</hi> For then he may come and challenge his right, and they cannot hinder him, pleading that he hath what is neceſſary to Church-memberſhip, <hi>viz.</hi> Cohabitation. Hence no Church would have Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:31515:32"/> to maintain any Purity of Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances and defend them from cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt communicants, according to the Rules of the Goſpel, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there would be no need of Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers and Diſcipline to this end. Beſides, Excommunication muſt be the Removal of men out of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, and nothing elſe: for it is the cutting a man off, from the bond of communion. Now if the Pariſh limits be the bond of Fellowſhip, then Excommunication muſt be the cutting a man off from it; but Chriſt never intended that Church Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline ſhould cut off any one from civil Rights and Properties<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh men.</p>
               <p>Yea there is nothing makes the Ordinances of Chriſt ſo cheap and contemptible as ſuch Church work as this, when there is no other Qualification required to adult Church-memberſhip, then cohabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation in the Precinct where ſuch
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:31515:32"/> pretended Church is; and this is ſo neceſſary an enforcing reaſon, that the Inhabitant cannot avoid it without the hazard of the greateſt Penalties from Church and State; neither can the Church refuſe him, making a Profeſſion of chriſtianity at large, though he be otherwiſe the greateſt known Debauchee in all manner of Wickedneſs; nor when he is admitted to communion be rid of him, according to the true Nature of this Rule, but by remov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him out of the Pariſh. And therefore I ſuppoſe this is the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Proceeding of ſuch that aſſert Pariſh-churches, that after Excommunication, upon non-return Offenders are committed to a Goal, a Severity that Chriſt and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles never thought of, but in a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Prophecy, when they foreſaw the cruelty and tyranny that would be exerciſed under the Antichriſtian Kingdom. Forcible and impos'd
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:31515:33"/> communion is nauſeous to all ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous minded men, in natural or civil Societies; no man will be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to be of a Family by way of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finity, nor of a Society by incorpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Nay there's no ſuch Society, Oeconomy, or Body corporate, but look upon it much beneath them to proſtitute their Rights and Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges to every Paultry Townſman or Inhabitant, much leſs will im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe them upon unwilling Perſons, though accounted never ſo wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, by this Bond of Church fellowſhip, <hi>viz. Cohabitation,</hi> a man is totally deprived of the uſe of his own Reaſon, Judgment and Conſcience in Spirituals, whereas all Laws leaves us to the uſe of them in temporal and civil affairs; for if a man is immediately of ſuch a Church, as ſoon as he hath rented a houſe, or took Lodgings in ſuch a Pariſh, the whilſt he inhabits
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:31515:33"/> there, he cannot upon any terms but of culpable Separation, joyn himſelf to another Church, where he may be more edifyed, tho' but a ſtones caſt from him. And if he was of the other Pariſh before, where he enjoyed God under an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Godly Miniſter, and in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of a faithful people; and doth upon family-neceſſity, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency of trade or dwelling, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move but into the next ſtreet over the Pariſh-bounds, where it may be in the next, is an ignorant, ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous, perſecuting and rayling Miniſter, and haply a people not unlike him; (which is no new thing, the Prophets tells us, <hi>Like Priests like People</hi>) he is neceſſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be a Profeſſed Member of this Synagogue of Satan, and cann't remain a Church-member of the former, by reaſon of his remove. And that this is ſo <hi>de facto,</hi> ſee <hi>Can.</hi> 28. entituled, <hi>Strangers not to be
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:31515:34"/> admitted to the Communion; <hi>Church-wardens,</hi>
                  </hi> &amp;c. <hi>ſhall obſerve, —Whether any Strangers come often and commonly from other Pariſhes to their Church, and ſhall ſhew their Miniſters of them, least perhaps they be admitted to the Lords Tahle a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt others, which they ſhall forbid, and remit ſuch home to their own Pariſh-Churches, and Miniſters; there to receive the Communion with their reſt of their Neighbours.</hi> Juſt as one Neighbour doth with the others Dogs, when they run into each other houſes a munching: <hi>Home you Cur you, &amp;c</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here's no admiſſion of Members of another Pariſh; therefore our concluſion holds good, That by this bond of Communion, Chriſtians are cut off from the free Election of their Miniſter, and Society in holy things: whereas he is not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thralled ſo in worldly matters; he can go out of the Pariſh to chooſe
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:31515:34"/> his Phyſician, Chirurgion, Wife, Nurſe, Apprentice, Taylor; Trade and deal for any Commodities where he will, excepting Spiritual, and in thoſe he muſt take no better (will he, nill he) then his own Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh-ſhop affords. Is not this ſo far from a Goſpel conſtitution of a Church, that it's a miſerable, wretched and damnable device of the Devil, to deſtroy the very na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Goſpel-Churches, and ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine poor Souls to all intents and purpoſes?</p>
               <p>I know what will be ſtill plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for a Pariſh Church, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect (ſome will it may be ſay) to the bond of Cohabitation; and that is this,</p>
               <p>That where-ever the Word and Sacraments are Adminiſtred, that is a true Church.</p>
               <p>To which I anſwer theſe things: 1. There is no politick Society but hath a bond of Union, and if that
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:31515:35"/> be proved null, void and of no ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, as we have done, the whole Society or Corporation falls to the ground; 2. <hi>That which is Sawce for a Gooſe, is for a Gander alſo;</hi> if the Preaching the Word, and Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring the Sacraments, make a Church without any more; why do the Aſſertors of Pariſh-Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es deny Separate Congregations, where the Word and Sacraments are Adminiſtred, to be ſuch? 3. There may be a Church in a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh where the VVord is Preached, and Sacraments Adminiſtred; but it follows not thence the Pariſh is the Church, It's poſſible there may be a Church of Chriſt in <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giers,</hi> but then it follows not that the City of <hi>Algiers</hi> is a Church; 4. The 19th. Can. of the Church of <hi>England</hi> ſaith, There ſhould be <hi>a Congregation of faithful men,</hi> and a <hi>due</hi> Adminiſtration, and the <hi>Word</hi> of God <hi>Purely</hi> Preached;
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:31515:35"/> Implying, that where the Majority at leaſt, which carries the denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the whole in all body po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticks, are not viſibly faithful men, but otherwiſe, there's not a Church of Chriſt: likewiſe where the word of God is <hi>corruptly</hi> Preached, and the Sacraments <hi>unduely</hi> admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred 5. A Miniſters Preaching by a meer Pariſh-relation, makes him no more a Paſtor, then coha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation makes the Pariſhioners Members; for a Miniſters Pariſh-relation is only a humane inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and indeed a matter of Civil Right, (which may be well im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved in Reformed Chriſtian Nations) in order to Spiritual Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage for the intereſt of Chriſt and his true conſtituted Churches, by the countenance of good Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates; but that it is a Church-relation ſetled on Goſpel-grounds, it would be abſurdly inſolent to pretend. That the eſtabliſhment of
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:31515:36"/> a Ruling Preaching Officer in the Church of Chriſt ſhould be, 1. by the Preſentation of a Forreigner, or a Tyrannical Gentleman or Landlord in the Pariſh, it may be the moſt profeſt Enemy to Chriſt and his Church; and if of the firſt ſort, by one that knows not the temper and diſpoſition of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, nor the Abilities, Parts and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty of him he Preſents; never regarding ſo much thoſe qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions whereby he might edify the people, but only ſome carnal ends and advantages, or particular re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to the Perſon of the Pariſh-Rector, to prefer him or provide a competency for his Subſiſtance. This man being preſented, is inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted and inducted, takes to the profits for his life, (unleſs he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit them by ſome Puritan or Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natick faults) performs Pariſh-du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties as the Law of ſome people re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires, this is his Pariſh-relation;
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:31515:36"/> but not in the leaſt grounded upon the Goſpel. 6. A Miniſter may Preach a great while in any place, to any ſort of people, before there is a Church; as for Converſion, or for tryal of his Gifts and Parts; but none can be ſo abſurd as to affirm that that conſtant Preaching ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders the Pariſh a Church: for we know by woful experience, that the word may be powerfully Preached in Pariſhes for a great while, and great part, moſt, or it may be all, be ſcarcely civilized, but remain in Profeſſed Atheiſm, or manifeſt Prophaneneſs; it may be, open Perſecuting Enmity to Godlineſs: And if any ſay it muſt be conſtant Preaching that muſt denominate the Pariſh a Church: I would know how long? And what time is required? If it be ſaid till ſome are brought home to Chriſt, and by a viſible Profeſſion to ſubmit to his Goſpel-Rules and
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:31515:37"/> Government, then the limits of the Church is no further then the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of the Goſpel, and it compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hends not thoſe Inhabitants that ſtill remain Profeſſed Rebels againſt Chriſt. So that if the Preaching the Goſpel in a Pariſh, renders it a Church of Chriſt, as ſuch, one Sermon will do it as well as a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred; I ſay if all the Pariſhioners, as ſuch, are to be the Church-mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers without exception, upon the Goſpel Preached. 7. A Miniſter is often ſent by Chriſtian Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, for Converſion of People; ſhall they preſently be a Church, whether they receive or own his Doctrine or no? And it may be none of them, or at leaſt moſt of the Pariſhioners, capable of judging of him or his Doctrine; or a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter ſometimes is impoſed by a Patron or Biſhops, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> upon a ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable people, ſhall they preſently fall into a Church-Relation, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:31515:37"/> they approve him and chooſe him or no? Such things carry the greateſt abſurdities with them. 8. As Preaching may be in a Pariſh, and no Conſtituted Church of Chriſt there, ſo there may be the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of Sacraments, and no Church of Chriſt there; and if there be in the Pariſh, it makes not the Pariſh a Church. Suppoſe a pretended Miniſter impoſed on a people that evidently enough de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares himſelf by his life and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine never to have been ſent of Chriſt, and challengeth the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh by vertue of Humane Laws to be his Church (as they call it) which in general, own no other Church-Relation, but by Cohabitation; this man goes on to Preach the Sentiments of his own Brain, abuſe Scripture, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach Godlineſs, rail at, Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute and devour the Sheep of
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:31515:38"/> Chriſt, if there be any; joyn in with the wicked, ignorant, lewd and debaucht part of the Pariſh, and do all he can to infect the reſt with the Scab or Rot; This man Baptizeth and Adminiſters the Lords Supper to his Infect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Flock, calls the ſoundeſt Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks and Separatiſts: Doth this conſtitute a Church of Chriſt, or a Synagogue of Satan? what are all his Admidiſtrations but an U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpation? As to the efficacy of the Act done, its not my Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince to determine here; I ſhall onely ſay as to the matter of Baptiſm, I roundly affirm, That I believe it no more effectual, than if a Cobler Tinker or Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wife had done it with ſome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent Solemnity. Hence it evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently may be concluded, That the Adminiſtration of Sacraments con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutes not a Church of Chriſt, much leſs makes a Pariſh a Church.
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:31515:38"/> But in the foremention'd inſtances, the whole proceeding of Miniſters and People are a meer uſurpation of Communion in Church Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, and is no better then <hi>Jero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boams</hi> worſhipping <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel,</hi> and Conformity thereto no better then the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> Conformity thereto in obedience to their lawful civil Governours, in that which is a declared Abomination to the Lord.</p>
               <p>Obj. <hi>You do hereby <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nchurch ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny an eminent Church, where there hath been a Faithful Parish Miniſter, and holy good people walking as his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rishioners in Communion with him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> We unchurch no true Church of Cbriſt by this means, for i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> one thing to ſay a thing is Church, and that it's occaſional of a Church. I deny not but many Miniſters Pariſh-Relation, and Peoples cohabitation, have been ocaſions of many Reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:31515:39"/> Churches, which Chriſt hath accepted in their degrees of Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation; but we affirm they were not Churches of Chriſt as ſuch, <hi>i. e.</hi> as Members of a Pariſh; but as a faithul people, related by a Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Bond of Union to Chriſt, and one to another, in Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the Word purely Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and Sacraments duely Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:31515:39"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Of the Catholick Viſible Church.</head>
               <p>THoſe that ſpeak of a Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Viſible Church, ſpeak ſome at one rate, and ſome at ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>If they mean that the Catholick Church is Viſible in the largeſt ſence, as ſuch, we deny it; for it is not viſible to us, nor can be, till all the Elect are called in, and ſo muſt be onely at <hi>the General Aſſembly and Church of the Firſt-born;</hi> for at preſent the moſt eminent part of it is triumphant; many true Believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers that are militant, not ſeen or known to us: And ſo to ſay the Catholick Church is Viſible, is to ſet our words and ſences at vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance.</p>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:31515:40"/>
               <p>By Catholick Viſible, ſome will ſay they mean not the whole Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Church, but ſo much of it as is viſible; but this cannot, for that reaſon, have the denomination of Catholick Church, becauſe its but a very ſmall part of it, and part cannot be called the whole; beſides if it be limited to the Viſible Saints militant, I ſay the univerſality of them are never viſible; either in any congregation, or in communion of any Ordinance, or under any Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Paſtoral Juriſdiction; neither are the particular Members of the <hi>Church</hi> militant viſible at the ſame time, there being no ſuch time when all true Believers are known by their viſible Profeſſion.</p>
               <p>Some underſtand by the <hi>Catholick Viſible Church,</hi> an Organized <hi>Church</hi> with a viſible Paſtoral Head, and furniſhed with Officers ſuiting a <hi>Catholick</hi> Ruling Power over all <hi>Churches</hi> and Saints on Earth; and
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:31515:40"/> this is the meaning alwayes of the Papiſts when they ſpeak of the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church,</hi> calling themſelves <hi>Catholicks</hi> as Members of it, which <hi>Church</hi> they ſay, <hi>Rome</hi> is, wherein this univerſal Paſtor and Juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is placed.</p>
               <p>But it is by a cloud of Witneſſes aſſerted that <hi>Chriſt</hi> never Ordained any univerſal viſible Paſtor, nor ever promoted <hi>Peter</hi> above the reſt of the Apoſtles, neither did ever the greateſt contender for the <hi>Popes Headſhip,</hi> and Supremacy over all other Paſtors and <hi>Churches,</hi> ever make ſeeming fair proof of it, for though he ſent ſorth his Apoſtles as extraordinary Officers, with an extraordinary preſence for working Miracles, and healing, in order to the firſt propagating the Goſpel, and Plantation of <hi>Churches,</hi> yet they had but a co-ordinate power, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther were they fixed as ſtanding and laſting Officers in the <hi>Church,</hi>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:31515:41"/> neither was their Apoſtolick pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er conveyed to any Succeſſors, but dyed with them, leaving only ordinary Officers in the Church. Laſtly, can you read the word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> any where to import in the New Teſtament, a <hi>Church</hi> of this nature, <hi>viz.</hi> a <hi>Catholick Viſible</hi> Organized <hi>Church. Chriſt</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pofitively forbad it, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved that ſpirit of Ambition; that was one thing that our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our ſaw working in them, labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be Dignitaries; <hi>But he that will be chief among you, let him be your Servant, Mat.</hi> 20.17. &amp; 23.11.10.24, 25. Which Reprimand the Mother of <hi>Zebedee</hi>'s children recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, when ſhe enquired who ſhould be greateſt among her children.</p>
               <p>There are ſix or ſeven ſorts of <hi>Churches</hi> in the latter dayes that entitle themſelves the <hi>Churches</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> which the Goſpel makes no mention of, <hi>viz. Catholick</hi> Orga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nized
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:31515:41"/> Viſible, ſuch the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> Patriarchal, National, Provincial, Dioceſan, Archdeconary, Parochial. Theſe ſeem to be <hi>the ſeven women ſpoken of, Iſa.</hi> 4.1. <hi>that ſhall take hold of one man [The Lord Jeſus Chriſt] Saying we will eat our own bread, and wear our own Apparel, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly let us be called by thy name to take away our reproach.</hi> They will have the name of Chriſt, that they may not be Reproached as the Churches of Antichriſt, and yet will be at their own proviſion for Worſhip and Ordinances by humane inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. But for all this, tho' theſe whoriſh women make a ſhift by a common vogue to carry the name of the True Goſpel Churches throughout the world, his True Spouſe, though ſmall and contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible as to outward appearance, ſhall be glorious, ver. 2. <hi>In that day the branch of the Lord ſhall be beautiful and glorious, and the fruit of the
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:31515:42"/> earth ſhall be excellent and comely for them that are eſcaped of</hi> Iſrael, ver. 3. <hi>And it ſhall come to paſs, that he that is left in Zion [in that great Aposta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy] and he that remaineth in</hi> Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem <hi>ſhall be called holy, even every one that is written among the living in</hi> Jeruſalem. See what follows from ver. 4. to the end.</p>
               <p>This I take to be the true mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of that place; for 1. Women in the Prophetick phraſe are Churches, as frequent inſtances may be given. 2. The number may be definite for an indefinite. 3. The Prophecy is manifeſtly of the latter dayes, and the Churches ſtate therein, which none will deny.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:31515:42"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> Of the moſt uſual acceptation of the word Church, in the New Teſtament.</head>
               <p>WE have ſhewed that in one place the word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for any common Aſſembly, lawful or unlawful, <hi>Acts</hi> 19.32, 39. and likewiſe that it's once ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for a National Church, <hi>Acts</hi> 7.38.</p>
               <p>But in all other places, it's ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther taken for the Univerſal <hi>Church</hi> of Chriſt, or for particular Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations; and for no other ſorts of Churches.</p>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:31515:43"/>
               <p>The Univerſal Church of Chriſt is one Organized Body, Chriſt being the Head, and all the Saints Trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant, and Militant, the Members; united together, either by a real Bond, viſible or inviſible, or both.</p>
               <p>This Church of Chriſt either is mentioned in the New Teſtament in the moſt general conſideration; or more particularly, referring to it in the myſtical part of it, or to the Viſible Externally Organized parts of it, which are the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Churches. I ſhall briefly go through the places of the New Teſtament, where it's uſed, for the Readers ſatisfaction. It is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for the Body of Chriſt under the moſt general and comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive ſignification, and ſo it's to be underſtood of a Body conſiſting of Head and Members, made up of viſible and inviſible, real and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing only.</p>
               <p>The places carrying it in this
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:31515:43"/> ſence, are, Mat. 16.18. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon this Rock will I build my Church, i. e.</hi> my whole Spiritual Fabrick ſhall be built upon that Perſon and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine which thou haſt born wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to in this Profeſſion.</p>
               <p>Epheſ. 1.22, 23. <hi>Hath put all things under his feet, and gave him to be Head over all things to his Church, which is his Body, the full<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of him that filleth all in all.</hi> Col. 1.24. <hi>Who now rejoyce in my Sufferings for you, and fill up that which is behind, of the Afflictions of Chriſt</hi> [myſtical] <hi>in my Flesh, for his Bodies ſake, which is the Church.</hi> Note that where the Church is called the Body of Chriſt, it is meant of the Univerſal <hi>Church</hi> for the moſt part.</p>
               <p>Eph. 3.10. <hi>To the intent that now unto Principalities and Powers in Heavenly Places, might be made known by the Church the manifold Wiſdom of God, i. e.</hi> by the whole
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:31515:44"/> Church both militant and trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant, by the eminent Grace and Glory ſhinning forth in them, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the admiration of Angels; even to ſee, ver. 9. <hi>The Fellowſhip of the Myſtery which from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the world hath been hid in God,</hi> &amp;c. And ver. 21. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto him be Glory in the Church by Jeſus Chriſt, throughout all Ages, world without end.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Epheſ. 5.25. <hi>He hath loved his Church, and given himſelf for it;</hi> ver. 27. <hi>to make it a glorious Church,</hi> 29. <hi>No man hateth his own fleſh, but nouriſheth it and cherisheth it, even as the Lord the Church, i. e.</hi> the whole Church; <hi>for we are Members of his body, of his flesh and his bones:</hi> ver. 32. <hi>This is a great Mystery, but I ſpeak of Chriſt and his Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Heb. 12.23. <hi>To the General Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly and Church of the firſt born,</hi> which muſt be underſtood of the Univerſal Church in its pureſt and
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:31515:44"/> moſt glorious ſtate, both militant and triumphant; to which every true Believer comes when he is u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited by Faith to Chriſt the Head. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> there is the only word in the New Teſtament can be rendred Catholick Aſſembly.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Church is taken in the New Teſtament for the viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble part of the Catholick <hi>Church,</hi> 1 Cor. 12.27, 28. <hi>Ye are the Body of Christ, and Members in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, and God hath ſet ſome in the Church firſt Apoſtles, then Prophets, &amp;c.</hi> In this and ſuch like places <hi>Church</hi> is taken primarily for the Univerſal <hi>Church,</hi> though there be many things applyed thereto, which more immediately belong to the viſible parts of it in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular ſimular Congregations, and differing Members, in reſpect of Office, Grace, or Gifts. And ſo i:'s to be underſtood in the place laſt quoted; as alſo, Eph. 4.11, 12, 13. a Parallel Place, and ſuch is, Rom. 12.4, 5, 6, 7.</p>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:31515:45"/>
               <p>Laſtly, 1 Tim. 3.15. <hi>That thou may'ſt know how to behave thy ſelf in the houſe of God, which is the Church of God, [i. e.</hi> in a particular part of the Univerſal <hi>Church] which is the pillar and ground of truth [i. e.</hi> the Univerſal Church is the pillar and ground of Truth in the world, to defend and maintain it, and hold forth the light of it; but every particular Church is a Candleſtick to hold the Candle of the Goſpel-Light, and Profeſſion, and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, among which Chriſt walks. Theſe are all the places ſo near as I can find, which have reference to the Catholick Church, where <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia,</hi> or <hi>Church,</hi> is mentioned, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs thoſe that ſpeak of <hi>Pauls</hi> Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting the Church, which may be underſtood not only actual Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting the Particular Church of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> but of the whole Body of Chriſt, becauſe 1. that Church was all as yet Planted, and 2. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:31515:45"/> Chriſt takes his rage and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity to be levyed and managed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his myſtical Body, Acts 9. <hi>Saul, Saul, why Perſecuteſt thou me?</hi> The places are theſe, 1 Cor. 15.9. Gal. 1.13. Phil. 3.6. Acts 8.3.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:31515:46"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> Of a Particular Church.</head>
               <p>I come in the next place to ſhew what the word Church impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in all other Texts of the New Teſtament, were it is uſed, not yet mentioned, which is far the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er part.</p>
               <p>And to make it evident, that no other Church is by them intended then ſuch an one which is deſcrib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the 19th Article of the Church of <hi>England, viz. A Church is a Congregation of Faithful Men, where the pure Word of God is Preached, and the Sacraments duly Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stred, according to Gods holy Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances;</hi>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:31515:46"/> which can have no other underſtanding, then that of a <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Church.</hi> I need not deſcant upon it, it carryes ſo much plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and correſpondency to the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuine ſence of a Church in all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Goſpel, where a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Church is intended, that there is no room for exception.</p>
               <p>The firſt Text is, Mat. 18.17. <hi>Tell the Church,</hi> which is the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Congregation of faithful men, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Its nonſence to ſuppoſe that a National or Provincial Church is here meant; that upon every offence between brother and brother, an addreſs muſt be made to a Council, Synod, Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop or Biſhop; and where have we Counſels or Synods, or Paſtors called Churches in any place of the New Teſtament? If any man pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>end to object that our Saviour here <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntended the Church of the Jews; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd that to tell the Church, was to
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:31515:47"/> tell the <hi>Sanhedrim:</hi> Let ſuch an one <hi>give</hi> one inſtance, that the <hi>Sanhedrim</hi> is called the Church in Old or New Teſtament; I am ſure not in the New: neither is it rational to ſuppoſe that our Saviour gave here Rules for the Oeconomy of the Jewiſh Church, which was ſo ſoon after to be diſſolved as to its whole conſtitution, our Saviour ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver intending the erection of a National Church more.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The next Texts are Acts 2.47.<note place="margin">Of the Church of Jeruſalem:</note> 
                  <hi>And the Lord added to the Church daily ſuch as ſhould be ſaved.</hi> This was without diſpute a particular Congregation, for there was as yet but that one, which was that CXX which Chriſt left together at his Aſcention. This was the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of the Faithful which was added to; which is the ſame Church that was ſpoken of, Acts 5.11. <hi>Fear fell upon all the Church, or Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:31515:47"/> of the Faithful.</hi> The firſt mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplying of Churches, was occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned by <hi>Sauls</hi> Perſecution, after the ſtoning of <hi>Stephen;</hi> ſcattering a great part of this Congregation, now grown too big for one: Acts 8.1, 3. <hi>There was a great Perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againſt the Church which was at Jeruſalem;</hi> againſt this Church in particular, <hi>Sauls</hi> Perſecution was breathed, which he mentions after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.9. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.13. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.6. after which he continues to breath out threatnings and ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and aſſay's to purſue them to <hi>Damaſcus,</hi> and other places, Acts 9.1. near which place Chriſt ſtops his Career.</p>
               <p>But notwitſtanding this ſcatter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, which God turn'd to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of the Goſpel, and encreaſe of Churches, by the Preaching of <hi>Philip</hi> and other ſcattered brethren, ſo that as chap. 8. and 11. ver. 19. and in ver. 21. <hi>The hand of the Lord
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:31515:48"/> was with them, and a great number were added to the Lord:</hi> So that in <hi>Judea,</hi> the Churches of <hi>Samaria,</hi> and <hi>Galilee,</hi> were gathered, <hi>Acts</hi> 9.31. It appears alſo the Body of that Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem-Church ſtill remained, &amp; ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings coming to them of the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellous ſucceſs of the Miniſtry of the ſcattered Diſciples, they ſent forth <hi>Barnabas,</hi> Acts 11.22: <hi>Then tyd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of theſe things came to the ears of the Church which was in</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>and they ſent forth</hi> Barnabas <hi>that he ſhould go as far as</hi> Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>och,<note place="margin">The Church of <hi>Antioch</hi>
                  </note> &amp;c. <hi>ver.</hi> 25. from thence he departed to <hi>Tarſus</hi> to ſeek <hi>Saul, ver.</hi> 26. And when he had found him he brought him to <hi>Antioch,</hi> and it came to paſs, <hi>that a whole year they Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled themſelves with the Church, and taught much people,</hi> i. e. beſides the Churches, this is the Firſt Goſpel-Church of the Gentiles we read of. Now that this was a Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:31515:48"/> of the Faithful, converted firſt by the Miniſtry of the Scat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, it appears in that <hi>Barnabas</hi> firſt fell upon confirming work, v. 23. <hi>When he came and had ſeen the Grace of God, was glad, and exhorted them all that with purpoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f heart they would cleave unto the Lord;</hi> and by his further labours the Church was encreaſed, v. 24. <hi>and much people were added unto the Lord;</hi> though I will not deny, this expreſſion may <hi>intend his first forming them into a</hi> Church, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the coming of <hi>Saul,</hi> after which we are aſſured it was a Formed Church ſeparated from the reſt of the people of <hi>Antioch,</hi> yea, from many that were frequent hearers of the Word, as appears verſe 26.</p>
               <p>After this a ſecond Perſecution ariſeth againſt the Church of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> Act. 12.1. <hi>Now about that time</hi> Herod <hi>the King ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:31515:49"/> forth his hands to vex certain of the Church, and killed</hi> James, <hi>and impriſoned</hi> Peter; <hi>for whom Prayer was made without ceaſing of the Church unto God for him;</hi> verſe 5, 12. <hi>viz.</hi> Aſſembled in a private Meeting.</p>
               <p>Chap 13.1. We have an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of <hi>Certain Prophets</hi> in the Church of <hi>Antioch,</hi> a ſort of extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Officers in the Primitive Churches, mentioned next after Apoſtles, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.11. Theſe were charged by the Holy Ghoſt to ſet apart <hi>Barnabas</hi> and <hi>Saul</hi> to the work whereunto he had called them, which being ſent forth, they went their Progreſs to <hi>Seleucia, Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prus, Salamis, Paphos, Perga</hi> in <hi>Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philia,</hi> and from thence to <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>och</hi> in <hi>Piſidia,</hi> chap. 13. verſe 14. there <hi>Paul</hi> preached in the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue with great acceptation of the Proſelyte <hi>Gentiles,</hi> who aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to hear the next Sabbath from
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:31515:49"/> all parts of the City; but the <hi>Jews contradicting and blaſpheming,</hi> they declare the rejection of the <hi>Jews, and there turn to the Gentiles,</hi> ver. 46, 47. Being Perſecuted from this <hi>Antioch they came to Iconium,</hi> to the <hi>great joy of the Diſciples,</hi> verſe 51, 52. Here they Preached with ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, chap. 14.1. but were oppoſed by the Unbelieving <hi>Jews,</hi> and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted to <hi>Lystra</hi> &amp; <hi>Derbe,</hi> verſe 20. <hi>Cityes of Lycaonia:</hi> At <hi>Lyſtra</hi> cured the Cripple, and like to be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped for Gods; but the <hi>Jews</hi> from <hi>Antioch and Iconium</hi> change the Scene, ver. 19. and <hi>Paul</hi> was ſtoned; but recovered, departed to <hi>Derbe,</hi> and after Preaching there, returned to <hi>Lystra, Iconium and Antioch of Piſidia,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Churches of</hi> Lyſtra, Iconium, Antioch <hi>of</hi> Piſidia.</note> 
                  <hi>confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Diſciples,</hi> verſe 22, 23. <hi>ordaining Elders in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Church.</hi> Theſe Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of <hi>Lyſtra, Iconium,</hi> and <hi>Antioch,</hi> were gathered at the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:31515:50"/> firſt coming, and at their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to confirm them, they ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Elders in them. Theſe were not National Churches; <hi>Antioch</hi> was of the Region of <hi>Piſidia;</hi> nor was the whole limit of any of theſe places of the Church, but a few of each that were wrought upon by, and ſubmitted to their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry. From <hi>Piſidia,</hi> they came to the Province of <hi>Pamphilia,</hi> ver. 24. where they Preached at <hi>Perga,</hi> went to <hi>Attalia,</hi> and thence ſailed to the firſt <hi>Antioch,</hi> where theſe two Apoſtles, ſo called ver. 14. were Ordained, and from whence they were ſent to this Apoſtolick work of gathering Churches, and ſetling Elders in them; here they give the Church of <hi>Antioch</hi> an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of what God had done by them, in opening a door of faith unto the Gentiles, verſe 27. and abode there a long time. During, their abode there, diſturbance was
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:31515:50"/> raiſed by ſome men that came from <hi>Judea,</hi> and taught the neceſſity of <hi>circumciſion,</hi> chap. 15.1, 2, 3. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the Apoſtles and certain o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers were ſent to <hi>the Apoſtles and Elders at</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>about this que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, and were brought on their way by the</hi> Church, verſe 3. I ſuppoſe none can conjecture that here was any Church beſides a Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Faithful; no Houſe-church, that could bring the Apoſtles on their way; no National or Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Church; it's not to be ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, that all the Province or City of <hi>Antioch</hi> accompanied them, but only thoſe few that were gathered into a Church; and they not ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken all in one Pariſh or Precinct of the City, but here and there, as it pleaſed God by his Grace to work. When they came, verſe 4. to <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> they were received <hi>by the Church, Apostles and Elders,</hi> where the queſtion was determined, verſe
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:31515:51"/> 22. and return made (with the reſolves of the Apoſtles and Church of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi>) to <hi>Antioch,</hi> and ſtaying ſome time there, confirmed the Diſciples. But ſome days af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> agreeing to depart to reviſit the Cities where they Preached, they diſagreed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout taking <hi>John Mark, and ſo</hi> parted; <hi>Paul</hi> then took <hi>Silas,</hi> and went through <hi>Syria and Cilicia, Barnabas took Mark and went to Cyprus;</hi> places where they had been, verſe 36, 37. confirming the Churches, v. 41. I ſhall proceed no further in theſe two Apoſtles travells; this being enough to ſhew what ſort of Churches were firſt planted by them; and to ſhew where any mention is made of Church, and that's but in two places more in the <hi>Acts,</hi> Acts 18.22. <hi>After he had Landed at</hi> Ceſarea,<note place="margin">Church of <hi>Caeſarea.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>and went up and ſaluted the Church, he went
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:31515:51"/> down to</hi> Antioch, <hi>and</hi> chap. 20.17. <hi>from</hi> Miletus<note place="margin">Miletus.</note> 
                  <hi>he ſent to</hi> Epheſus <hi>and called the Elders of the Church, and charged them,</hi> v. 28. <hi>Take heed therefore to your ſelves, and to all the Fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ck, over which the Holy Ghoſt hath made you Overſeers, to feed the Church of God, which he hath purchaſed with his Blood.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now what were theſe but ſuch Congregations that accompany<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Apoſtles, that was ſaluted by them; that they confirmed, and were purchaſed by Chriſts blood; is it ſence to think they were Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, or whole Nations, or Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, or Cities? no they were thoſe faithful ones,<note place="margin">Building of living ſtones.</note> who being gathered into particular Congregations by the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry firſt of the Prophets, (<hi>i. e.</hi> the ſcattered Brethren from <hi>Jeruſalem</hi>) were ſetled and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by the Apoſtles, who Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained Officers reſpectively a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them.</p>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:31515:52"/>
               <p>I proceed in the next place to the Churches to whom the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Epiſtles were wrote.</p>
               <p>We read not the word Church in any part of the Epiſtles to the <hi>Romans,</hi> but in the 16th chapter, and there referring to other Churches,<note place="margin">The Church of the <hi>Romans.</hi>
                  </note> as verſe 1. he ſpeaks of <hi>Phebe</hi> a Deaconeſs of the Church at <hi>Cenchrea,</hi> and verſe 4: mentions all the Churches of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> verſe 5. ſalutes the Church in <hi>Aquila</hi>'s houſe, verſ. 16. <hi>The Churches of Christ ſalute you.</hi> Though we have reaſon enough to believe that there was at this time a conſtituted Church at <hi>Rome,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe firſt he writes to them as <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved of God, and called to be Saints,</hi> chap. 1. verſe 7. Secondly, becauſe he gives Rules to them for walking towards each other as thoſe in Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip, chap. 14. Thirdly, <hi>Phebe</hi> is recommended to them from the
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:31515:52"/> Church at <hi>Cenchrea,</hi> which would not have been, had they not been a Church.</p>
               <p>In the Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> we have more mention made of the word <hi>Church</hi> then in any E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle,<note place="margin">The Church of <hi>Corinth.</hi>
                  </note> importing a Particular Congregation; and we may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with that deſcription the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle gives of it, 1 Cor. 1.2. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto the Church of God which is at</hi> Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth, <hi>to them that are ſanctified in Chriſt Jeſus, called to be Saints, &amp;c.</hi> he writes not to all the Inhabitants of <hi>Corinth,</hi> but to the Church, which he tells you what they are, <hi>ſanctified in Chriſt Jeſus, called to be Saints;</hi> which words are exegeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal of Church; ſo he directs his ſecond Epiſtle, 2 Cor. 1.1. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto the Church of God which is at</hi> Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth, <hi>with all the Saints which are in all</hi> Achaia: <hi>Corinth</hi> was a City of the Province of <hi>Achaia,</hi> and he writes
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:31515:53"/> primarily to the Church at <hi>Corinth,</hi> and likewiſe to all the Saints which were in that Province, whether they were actually in Church Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip or no. I ſhall briefly men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion all the other Texts where Church is taken plainly for ſuch a Particular Congregation as is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed in the firſt Epiſtle, chap. 1.</p>
               <p>1 Cor. 4.17. <hi>I have ſent unto you</hi> Timotheus, — <hi>who ſhall bring you into remembrance of my ways which be in Chriſt, as I teach every where in every Church;</hi> i. e. every particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Congregation.</p>
               <p>1 Cor. 6.4. <hi>If then you have judgment of things appertaining to this life, ſet them to judge who are least eſteemed in the Church;</hi> i. e. in the Church of the <hi>Corinths,</hi> of them its primarily intended, and as a rule for other particular Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, where no ſuch thing as Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian civil Magiſtrates was in thoſe times. 1 Cor. 7.17. <hi>As the Lord
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:31515:53"/> hath called every one, ſo let him walk and ſo ordain I in all the Churches,</hi> i. e. as a Rule for every particular member of each Church.</p>
               <p>1 Cor. 11.16. <hi>If any man ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to be contentious, we have no ſuch Cuſtom, nor the Churches of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Verſe 18. <hi>When you come together in the Church,</hi> [i. e. the Aſſembly, not meant of the meeting place, as before noted; the ſame ſence as in verſe 22.]</p>
               <p>Chap. 14.4. <hi>He that Propheſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Edifieth the Church,</hi> i. e. <hi>the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation that heareth him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And verſe 5. his reaſon of prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Prophecying is given, <hi>viz. That the Church may receive Edifying;</hi> therefore ſaith, verſe 12. <hi>Seek that ye may excel, that the Church may receive Edifying;</hi> and verſe 19. <hi>In the Church I had rather ſpeak five words with my <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding that I might teach others.</hi> Verſe 23. <hi>If the whole Church be come together in one place.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:31515:54"/>
               <p>Verſe 28. <hi>If there be no Interpreter, let him keep ſilence in the Church,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Verſe 33. <hi>God is not the Author of Confuſion, but of Peace; as in all the Churches of the Saints.</hi> Verſe 34. <hi>Let your Women keep ſilence in the Churches.</hi> Verſe 35. <hi>For it is a ſhame for Women to ſpeak in the Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Chap. 16.1. <hi>Concerning the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection for the Saints, as I have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Order to the Churches</hi> [ſuch as are in the Province] <hi>of Galatia, even ſo do ye.</hi> Where ſhould Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lections be made, but in particular Congregations? Verſe 19. <hi>The Churches of</hi> Aſia, [i. e. of that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion] <hi>ſalute you;</hi> Aquila <hi>and</hi> Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcilla <hi>ſalute you, and the Church in their Houſe;</hi> it may be that fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently aſſembled there, or that was for the moſt part belonging to their Family; there might be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for a competent Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in ſuch times as thoſe: that Church is mentioned more times.</p>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:31515:54"/>
               <p>2 Cor. 8.1. <hi>We do you to wit of the Grace of God bestowed on the Churches of Macedonia;</hi> the word is always uſed in the plural Number, when its applyed to Nations, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces [<hi>Macedonia</hi> was a Province] Regions, as of <hi>Galatia, Macedonia, Aſia, Judea.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Verſe 18, 19. <hi>We have ſent with him the Brother whoſe praiſe is in the Goſpel throughout all the Churches,</hi> verſe 19. <hi>And not that only, but who were alſo choſen of the Churches to travel with us;</hi> the word is, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and might be rendred ordained, as well as in other places.</p>
               <p>Verſe 23. <hi>They are Meſſengers of the Churches.</hi> Verſe 24. <hi>Wherefore ſhew to them and before the Churches the proof of your Love.</hi> Chap. 11.8. <hi>I robbed other Churches to ſerve you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>2 Cor. 11.28. <hi>That which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth upon me daily, the care of all the Churches,</hi> viz. as to his Apoſtolical Office.</p>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:31515:55"/>
               <p>2 Cor. 12, 13. <hi>What is it wherein you are inferiour to other Churches.</hi> It ſeems there's no ſuperiority of one particlar Church above another, but are all co-ordinate.</p>
               <p>The word is thrice uſed in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Gallatians,</hi> Chap. 2.1, 2. <hi>Paul an Apoſtle — and all the Brethren which are with me, unto the Churches of</hi> Galatia [a Province] Verſe 13. <hi>You have heard of my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, how that beyond meaſure I perſecuted the Church of God, and wasted it; i. e.</hi> the Church of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> which was only extant when he began his Perſecution; and for ought I know, while it laſted, for that was a principal oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſional cauſe of ſcattering the <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> Church, in order to Propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation; but he tells them of more Churches in the Province of <hi>Judea,</hi> after his Converſion. Verſe 21, 22. <hi>Afterwards I came into the Regions
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:31515:55"/> of</hi> Syria <hi>and</hi> Cilicia, <hi>and was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known by face unto the Churches of</hi> Judea, <hi>which were in Christ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Apoſtle directs the Epiſtle to the <hi>Eph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſians</hi> thus, <hi>To the Saints which are at Epheſus, and to the faithful in Chriſt Jeſus;</hi> which terms have a ſynonymous accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion moſt times with a Church, and we have ground enough to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve there was an Eſtabliſhed Church there when <hi>Paul</hi> wrote, he writing of ſuch high myſteries concerning Chriſt and his <hi>Church;</hi> but we are fully aſſured of it after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, when <hi>John</hi> wrote, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.1. where he directs his Epiſtle to the <hi>Epheſian Church,</hi> as if to the <hi>Dutch,</hi> or <hi>French</hi> Church in <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> or the <hi>Epheſian</hi> Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on at <hi>Epheſus;</hi> but in all places where <hi>Church</hi> is mentioned in this Epiſtle, he treats only of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church, as hath been ſhewed, being his deſign moſtly to ſhew the
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:31515:56"/> Beauty, Glory and Myſtery of Chriſt Myſtical, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He directs his Epiſtle to <hi>Philip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pi</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Church of <hi>Philippi.</hi>
                  </note> in the ſame manner, and mentions the word Church but twice; the firſt is where he ſpeaks of his <hi>Zeal in Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting the Church,</hi> i. e. of <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> Philip. 3.6. and 4.15. where he ſaith, <hi>No Church communicated with me as to giving and receiving, but ye only:</hi> So that the Saints at <hi>Philippi</hi> were the Church.</p>
               <p>The Epiſtle to <hi>Coloſs,</hi> is directed <hi>to the Saints and faithful Brethren in Chriſt who are at</hi> Coloſs,<note place="margin">Church of <hi>Coloſs.</hi>
                  </note> chap. i, 2. <hi>i. e.</hi> the Congregation of the faithful there where this Epiſtle was to be firſt read, and then in the Church <hi>of Laodicea,</hi> chap. 4.16. He menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons alſo the <hi>Church in the Houſe of</hi> Nymphas; every where elſe the word relates to the <hi>Catholick Church</hi> in this Epiſtle, as hath been ſhewed.</p>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:31515:56"/>
               <p>The Apoſtle directs his ſecond Epiſtle to the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> verſe 1. <hi>To the Church of the Theſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalonians,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Church of <hi>Theſſalonica.</hi>
                  </note> and ſuch a Church as took their pattern from the Churches of God in <hi>Judea,</hi> 1 Theſſ. 2.14. and therefore he ſaith 2 Theſſ. 1.4. <hi>We our ſelves glory in the Churches of God for their Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and Faith in all our Perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Epiſtle to <hi>Timothy</hi> ſpeaks of particular Churches, 1 Tim. 3.5. <hi>If a man know not how to rule his own Houſe, how ſhall he take care of the Church of God,</hi> i. e. ſuch a one as falls under a Paſtoral care in a mans capacity of Government, as a Family doth; and 1 Tim. 5.16. <hi>Let not the Church be charged;</hi> that is, the particular Congregation, where Church charges ariſe, as the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text ſhews.</p>
               <p>In the Epiſtle to <hi>Philemon</hi> he ſpeaks of the <hi>Church in his Houſe,</hi>
                  <pb n="96" facs="tcp:31515:57"/> i. e. that did uſually aſſemble there, as indeed all the Church-Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies were in thoſe times in private Houſes, and this is the third Church in a private Family that is expreſly mentioned by <hi>Paul;</hi> there was <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quila</hi>'s, <hi>Nymphas</hi>'s and <hi>Philemon</hi>'s.</p>
               <p>The Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> hath the word Church but twice, the firſt is, chap. 2.12. <hi>I will declare</hi> thy <hi>Name unto my Brethren in the midſt of the</hi> Church, <hi>I will ſing Praiſe unto thee;</hi> a place taken out of the Pſalms, where in the next and Primary Signification, the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt, ſo far as he means himſelf, its to be underſtood of a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Congregation, where God is praiſed; and ſo far as its Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetically applyed to Chriſt, its meant of the Catholick Church; in the fore-going verſe, ſaying, <hi>He that ſanctifieth and who they are ſanctified, are all one: for which
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:31515:57"/> ſake he is not aſhamed to call them bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, ſaying,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And chap. 12.23. He <hi>ſpeaks ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly</hi> of the Catholick without diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> ſpeaks of the Elders of a particular Church ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly, <hi>James</hi> 5.14.</p>
               <p>So <hi>John</hi>'s third Epiſtle, verſe 6, 9, 10.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>John</hi> in the <hi>Revelations</hi> makes mention of the Word in the ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar and plural number, no leſs then nineteen or twenty times; and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways to be underſtood of particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Churches. I will only name the Texts that the Reader may inſpect at his Leiſure. <hi>Revel.</hi> 1.4, 11, 20. <hi>Chap.</hi> 2.1, 7, 8, 12, 17, 18, 23, 29. <hi>Chap.</hi> 3.1, 6, 7, 13, 14, 22. <hi>Chap.</hi> 22.16.</p>
               <p>I find the word Church uſed in the New Teſtament, about 85 times in this ſence, <hi>viz.</hi> of a particular Congregation, and cannot by any
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:31515:58"/> candid Reader be ſuppoſed to have any other meaning, nor with the leaſt ſhew of reaſon, be underſtood of any Meeting-houſe, National, Provincial, Dioceſan, or Parochial conſtitution, but only of a Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of Saints by mutual conſent ordinarily aſſembling together, for Attendance on Chriſt in all his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:31515:58"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> Of the Inferences neceſſary from the Fore-going Chapter.</head>
               <p>IT being diſcovered in what ſences the word Church is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in the New Teſtament; its an idle and vain thing for Chriſtians to trouble and concern their heads and Conſciences about humorſome conceipts and imaginations of mens brains; managed for the moſt part to ſerve their carnal Intereſts, or darken the Truth. Let men give up themſelves and Underſtandings im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partially to the plain, and genuine Sence and meaning of the Spirit of God, without ſqueezing or wreſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it to a deſign or prejudicate O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, or favouring any beloved Luſt, and the truth of the Goſpel
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:31515:59"/> would ſhine with full Evidence and Demonſtration. And therefore not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding mens great ſwelling and words of Vanity from Pulpit and Preſs, in matters of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, we ſhall make bold to lay down theſe following Aſſertions as undeniable plain Concluſions from what hath been ſpoken.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That the Goſpel Church E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed by our Lord Jeſus Chriſt in the dayes of the New Teſtament, is or can be no where underſtood of any other Church then the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church, or particular Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations of faithful men, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and that there is no one place that can have any fair pretence to be underſtood of any other conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Churches.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That where-ever the word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is uſed, it always ſignifies a Congregation or Aſſembly of men met together, at leaſt occaſionally, upon ſome civil, ſpiritual, or ſinful
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:31515:59"/> Account; and that we need not be beholding to any Tropical Sences, or ungrounded ſuppoſal of things, and meanings of Words, ſo remote, when in the plain and ordinary way of Underſtanding, things preſent themſelves to our Reaſons and Senſes; If we be not blinded with Pride, Paſſion, Prejudice, and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrangement from the true way of Spiritual Underſtanding, by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring Scripture with Scripture, and conſonacy of things to the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalogy of Faith.</p>
               <p n="3">3. We infer, That a Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of faithful men is the generi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal material part of a Church, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it comprehends all the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that is ever found in any Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel Church of any kind; all fit matter for ſuch a Congregation, are ſuch as are really ſo, or viſibly, <hi>(in foro mundi)</hi> or both. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, becauſe there is no Church of Chriſt ſpoken of, or mentioned in
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:31515:60"/> Old or New Teſtament, but is ſo called under the Notion of being a Congregation to be ſometime or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Aſſembled all together; the Catholick Church is ſo under that Notion, as being all gathered to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether actually and myſtically in Chriſt, and ſhall all appear one day in a glorious Congregation, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.22, 23. Where <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is to be underſtood as <hi>R. St.</hi> ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders it, <hi>Publicus conventus,</hi> a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Publick Aſſembly: likewiſe, wherever the Spirit of God ſpeaks of a Church of his own conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, its always ſo.</p>
               <p>The Old Teſtament Church was called ſo under that notion; though National, yet was required to be ſtill Congregational; all the Males being required thrice a year to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear before the Lord in a Viſible Congregation at the Tabernacle; (therefore called the Tabernacle of the Congregation) or at the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:31515:60"/> where it was in ſtanding; and it is ſo often called the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of the children of <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el;</hi> the Reader may turn to theſe places at leiſure, <hi>Exod.</hi> 16.2.10. <hi>Levit.</hi> 4.13. <hi>ch.</hi> 14.2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 20.1, 22. <hi>Joſ.</hi> 18.1. ch. 22.12, 16, 18. 2 Chr. 6.3. <hi>Ezra.</hi> 2.64. And the whole Congregation together 42360: theſe more or leſs made up one Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, theſe were Preached to by <hi>Ezra;</hi> and whatever the number of the Nation was, they were to meet all together in one place. And ſo we have the word applyed to the Church in the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that it alwayes ſignifies a Congregation that doth ordinarily meet together for their edification, if it be meant of a Particular Church; but if an Univerſal, ſuch a Church as ſhortly ſhall Aſſemble, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ſit together in a laſting ſinleſs and uninterrupted communion. So that a true Church of Chriſt under
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:31515:61"/> whatever Notion you take it, muſt be and is a Congregation of Saints, viſible, inviſible, or both, that do meet together in one place, for the Worſhip of God in Chriſt, and communion in one body.</p>
               <p n="4">4. We infer that we have part of the differencing form in that De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription, <hi>viz.</hi> where the pure word is Preached, and Sacraments duely Adminſtred, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for it diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the true Church, diſtinguiſheth the true viſible Churches from falſe and erroneous, it diſtinguiſheth a particular Church from the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, for there is no Church but a particular Congregation capable of having the word preached to it, and Sacraments duely adminiſtred in one Congregation, but a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Church; when the Catholick Church aſſembles, there will be nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p n="5">5. We find not the leaſt word in Old or New Teſtament, of a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentative
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:31515:61"/> Congregation, or Church-Repreſentative; the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of the <hi>Jews</hi> was to be by a Perſonal Appearance of all the Males, the Females were exempted upon Gods ſpecial Diſpenſation, by reaſon of their unfitneſs for Travel, as from circumciſion by reaſon of incapacity. But we find that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry viſible Church of Chriſt ſtill appeared before the Lord perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, for actual communion in Church Ordinances, in that way and method that God appointed in his Reſpective Diſpenſations; and we are fully aſſured there is no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentative Church of Chriſts in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, either Councels, or Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nods, or Presbyteries. We read not of any Presbytery, <hi>i. e.</hi> Aſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciation of Elders called the Church, but the Church is always ſpoken of diſtinctly from them. If there had been any Reaſon to have called any Elderſhip the Church, there
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:31515:62"/> had been Reaſon to have called that ſo in the Apoſtolick Church, which had ſo many famous Apoſtles, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and Evangeliſts in in it; but they are named diſtinctly in that great Councel held at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> Act. 15.22. <hi>It pleaſed the Apoſtles and Elders, with the whole Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. The Univerſal Church doth comprehend all the particular Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations in all Ages and places, (being ſimular and co-ordinate parts of it) of the viſible Saints, where (by the Inſtitution of Chriſt the Head) all the Ordinances are placed, and by his influence there is a ſupply of Graces and gifts, for the Edification of his Body, as like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe all Officers, and Offices, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.11, 12. of which there were <hi>Extraordinary and Ordinary.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. The extraordinary Officers were inſtituted for an extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Occaſion, <hi>viz.</hi> the firſt Planta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Goſpel-churches: They
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:31515:62"/> were <hi>Apoſtles, Prophets, Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts;</hi> the <hi>call</hi> of theſe, <hi>the works and Qualifications, was extraordinary:</hi> Theſe continued no longer than the firſt Age of the Church.</p>
               <p n="8">8. The Ordinary remaining Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers are no more than <hi>Presbyters,</hi> (which ſome make a little diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of) <hi>Paſtors, Teachers, Ruling Elders,</hi>) but there is no need of multiplication of Titles and Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, where the work doth ſo much correſpond, and is of the ſame na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) <hi>and Deacons;</hi> the firſt ſort to give themſelves principally to Prayer, and the Miniſtry of the Word, and Government: the latter to mind the matters of more exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal concern, called <hi>Tables,</hi> as the neceſſities of the Poor, the provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Elements for Sacraments, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniencies for Church-aſſemblies, and whatever is neceſſary upon ſuch Occaſions. Theſe Officers are no where found with a capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:31515:63"/> to exert their Power as <hi>ſuch,</hi> but in particular Congregations; tho' they be members of the Catholick Church, they are not Catholick Officers; Chriſt is now the only Catholick Officer, being the Head of the whole Body.</p>
               <p n="9">9. All the Officers of the Goſpel-church were placed in the one Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church, primarily and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately relating to Chriſt Myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, ſecondarily and mediately, to the ſeveral viſible militating parts thereof in particular Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and their Office-work was ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the planting and gathering in to them, or for the edification of thoſe gathered: The Extraordinary had an extraordinary call, furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with an extraordinary meaſure of the Spirit, as with an extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Commiſſion: the Ordinary had not theſe, but ſufficient both of the Spirit and commiſſion for anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſts glorious ends and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:31515:63"/> in building his Church in fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Ages, and gathering more.</p>
               <p n="10">10. It appears that the true actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al members of the viſible Church are viſible Saints and Believers, none that were adult were ever counted ſo in the Goſpel-ſence, but under-the Notion of the Profeſſion of Faith and Practice of Holineſs. True Faith makes a man a true Member of the myſtical Body of Chriſt, but cannot inſtate a man <hi>in foro Eccleſiae,</hi> in the rights of viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble communion, till it manifeſts it ſelf with credibility unto thoſe to whom the Preſervation of theſe Rights and Priviledges are commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, the actual Officers and Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of a viſible Church. The Rule that Chriſt hath given for knowing and judging of others is by their Fruits, and if the Church be miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for want of Infallibility, (which the Apoſtles themſelves came ſhort in, <hi>Simon Magus</hi> and <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi>
                  <pb n="110" facs="tcp:31515:64"/> being not known to them but by the Diſcovery of overt Acts) God chargeth them not culpably with it, that being a Prerogative that Chriſt reſerves to himſelf, and none ever Pretended to it but the falſe Prophet, the great Spiritual Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per; and it appears that our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our reſerved this Diadem to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in the <hi>Embrio</hi> of the Goſpel-church, by his Behaviour towards <hi>Judas,</hi> admitting him to viſible com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, meerly upon an outward Profeſſion, though he knew his Heart; leaving his Practice as an Example to his Miniſters and Churches; carrying himſelf as a viſible Paſtor, and dealt with men in the caſe of receiving to, or reject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from communion, according to the viſibility of their Profeſſion: therefore leaving it as a ſtanding Rule to his Church for future proceeding in this kind; not that he eſteemed Hypocrites any part
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:31515:64"/> of his myſtical Body, but yet the preſent Profeſſion giving them by his own Rules a right to all Exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Priviledges, and a Reputation, nothing inferiour to others; he ſpeaks of them in ſome Phraſes which to minds not throughly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in the Truth, create much difficulty, as John 17.11. <hi>Holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, keep through thy name thoſe whom thou haſt given me, that they may be one as we are;</hi> i. e. all thoſe that thou haſt given me to be of my myſtical Body, that they may be united in Participation of the Divine Nature, as we are one; verſ. 12. <hi>While I was with them in the World</hi> [as a viſible Paſtor among them] <hi>I kept them in thy Name; of thoſe thou gaveſt me,</hi> [that is the charge of, as a viſible Paſtor, and that I took upon their viſible Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion,] <hi>I have loſt none but the Son of Perdition.</hi> So John 15.2. <hi>Every branch in me</hi> [in the Church
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:31515:65"/> by a viſible Profeſſion] <hi>that beareth not fruit, he taketh away:</hi> verſe 6. <hi>If a man abide not in me, he is caſt forth as a branch and withered.</hi> So 1 John 2.19. <hi>They went out from us,</hi> [as a viſible Church] <hi>but were not of us;</hi> as part of the Catholick Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy.</p>
               <p n="11">11. Churches of Chriſt are and may be in Nations, Provinces, Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes, Pariſhes, though thoſe li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits of co-habitation are not ſo, as ſuch; <hi>Jeruſalem, Corinth, Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>och, Epheſus, Smyrna, Coloſs,</hi> &amp;c. were not Churches as ſuch, though there was a Church or Churches, in each of thoſe Towns or Cities, therefore we read of the Church in <hi>Corinth,</hi> and when he ſpeaks of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces or larger Tracts, he ſaith the Churches of ſuch a place, in the plural number, <hi>viz.</hi> Churches of <hi>Galatia, Macedonia, Judea,</hi> &amp;c. and therefore, the Language of the Spirit of God now, if he ſpake as
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:31515:65"/> then, would be to ſay, The Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of <hi>England, France, Spain,</hi> and not the Church, ſuppoſing all the Churches in ſuch a Province or Nation, to be Organized into one Body, under one viſible Paſtor, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our corrupt Dialect and Underſtanding.</p>
               <p n="12">12. Hence laſtly it is manifeſt that however it came to paſs that by the ſubtile inſinuation of the Myſtery of Iniquity, ſeveral An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian Fabricks have had the Reputation of the Churches of Chriſt; yet it appearing that they are nothing ſo indeed by Chriſts conſtitution; They are juſtly ſeparated from by all truely informed in the mind and will of Chriſt: And that this Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration is ſo far from being any thing of Schiſm, or culpable Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration, that it is a high and Eminent Duty, that all they that
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:31515:66"/> are growing up to the Stature of the Fulneſs of Chriſt, ſhould be ambitious of; and they need not fear the Unchurching of them, that Chriſt never made Churches.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:31515:66"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> Of the Bond of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion in the Church.</head>
               <p n="1">1. WE have ſhewed that the Church of Chriſt is of the Nature of a Body-corporate, whether conſidered in its <hi>mystical <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r viſible State;</hi> and therefore muſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ave a Bond of Union, there being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o body Phyſical or Politick, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ath ſome peculiar Bond that u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ites all the parts, whether ſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r or diſſimular, into one Body; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e <hi>Integrum</hi> or whole being made <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p of all parts, brought into mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>al conjunction and communion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y the ſaid common <hi>Nexus,</hi> which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Principle of the Life, Office,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:31515:67"/> Motion, and Action of each part in its due Reſpect to the whole.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Church of Chriſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing under this twofold conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Catholick and Viſible, in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Congregations and Polities, we muſt look upon the Bond or <hi>Nexus</hi> to be agreeable to each con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, the Spirit of God having ſo adjuſted it.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Hence the <hi>Spirit of Chriſt</hi> is the real true fundamental and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſſoluble Bond of Union, in this Catholick Body, between Chriſt and his Church, and every part and member thereof in Heaven and in Earth, in all Ages and Nations of the World; ſo that this, whether viſible or inviſible, is all but one Body: though as for the viſible part, in all Ages attended with va<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rious Manifeſtations, Diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and Regiments, according a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſt in his infinite Wiſdom wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pleaſed to carry on, and reveal the
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:31515:67"/> Glory of his Goſpel-myſteries in the World.</p>
               <p>Three States of the Church for its Oeconomy, hath appeared.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>First,</hi> In Families, as it conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued from the beginning of the world, till the increaſe of <hi>Abrahams</hi> Family into a Nation; and then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſe by ſome ſteps to a National Typical Church, by Chriſts own conſtitution, furniſhed with a high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Degree of Glory then the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer State, and inferiour to what was to follow.</p>
               <p>The third and laſt, was of all moſt clear, perfect, and glorious; which was the Goſpel Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, freed from Vails, Types, Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures, Shadows, both in reſpect of the true Doctrine, leading to Life and Salvation, the Sun of Righteouſneſs ſhining forth in his full Brightneſs, no way over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhadowed and in reſpect of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and Order of his Houſe,
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:31515:68"/> wherein he excell'd all that <hi>Moſes,</hi> or any before him, could do, in right Ordinances and Statutes, for the managing the Form and Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof</p>
               <p n="4">4. This Bond of Union is pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly myſtical, and no more viſible than the Vital or rather Animal Spirits, that vivifies the whole man in uniting the Soul and Body toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, whereby every part conjoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed is quickned and inabled to Act in its due place and kind; this we ſay is the Spirit of Chriſt, as it will appear from the expreſs words of the Scripture; 1 Cor. 12.3. <hi>I give you to understand, that no man ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by the Spirit of God, calleth Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus accurſed: and that no man ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſay Jeſus is the Lord, but by the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Verſe 4. <hi>Now there be diverſit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of Gifts, but the ſame Spirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Verſe 5. <hi>And there are difference of Adminiſtrations</hi> under the O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="119" facs="tcp:31515:68"/> and New Teſtament, <hi>but the ſame Lord,</hi> and Head of the Church; therefore the ſame Church Eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial.</p>
               <p>Verſe 6. <hi>There are Diverſities of Operations;</hi> [as in diſtinct Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, which operate according to their particular Forms and Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures] <hi>but it is the ſame God that worketh all in all,</hi> i. e. God by the ſame Spirit. Verſe 7. <hi>To another Faith by the ſame Spirit</hi> [to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of Faith of Miracles, or more then ordinary meaſures of Saving Faith, exerting it ſelf in an eminent manner, as <hi>Abrahams</hi> did, in particular trying caſes.] <hi>To ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the gift of healing by the ſame Spirit;</hi> [he goes on to enumerate not only the extraordinary, but or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary gifts and graces of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; thoſe given forth in the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Times, and thoſe that are ſince continued, and ſaith verſ. 11. <hi>All theſe worketh that one and the
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:31515:69"/> ſelf ſame Spirit, dividing to every man ſeverally as he will;</hi> and then he goes on to tell us that the Spirit doth not only diffuſe it ſelf throughout, and influence all the Members, from the Head with eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Gift and Grace, but that it ties all the Members together, to Chriſt the Head, and one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; verſ. 12. <hi>For as the Body</hi> [i. e the Natural Body] <hi>is one, and hath many Members, and all the Members of that one Body, being many, are one Body,</hi> [i. e. Myſtical] verſ. 13. <hi>For by one Spirit are we all baptized into one Body, whether we be Jews or Gentiles</hi> [the Jews before Chriſts coming were baptized ſpiritually into this Myſtical Body] <hi>whether we be bond or free; and have been all made to drink into one Spirit</hi> [i. e. all partakers of the operations and influences of one Spirit, in Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration and Juſtification.] Now ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſhewed that the Spirit unites
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:31515:69"/> the many Members into one Body, and is the common <hi>Nexus,</hi> he goes on to ſhew from whence the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity of parts, in form, ſhape, uſe and office doth ariſe, and the harmony and agreement; yea the neceſſity of this variety in kinds and degrees for the good of the whole, verſ. 14. <hi>For the Body is not one Member but many, &amp;c.</hi> and verſ. 24. <hi>God hath tempered the Body together [viz.</hi> with this diverſity of Gifts, of Parts, of Knowledg] For what end? To make a Schiſm? No, but that the <hi>deficient parts ſhould have the more honour, verſe</hi> 24. and not be trampled upon, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed and expoſed to ſhame; and verſe 25. <hi>That there ſhould be no Schiſm in the Body,</hi> but that the Members ſhould have the ſame care one of another, yea a ſympa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy and fellow-feeling ſhould be eſtabliſhed among all Parts, verſe 26. much leſs any hatred, deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:31515:70"/> and enmity betwixt them.</p>
               <p>We argue then, That which works all Gifts and Graces, and knits together all the Members, diverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyes all the Parts, and brings them into an harmonious office and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement for the good of the whole Myſtical Body of Chriſt under the Old and New Teſtament, is the Bond of Union of that Body; but it appears the Spirit of Chriſt doth this; <hi>Ergo</hi> it's the Catholick Bond. I might mention many other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, I'll only name two or three more.</p>
               <p>Eph. 4.1. The Apoſtle exhorts <hi>to walk worthy of their vocation,</hi> and mentioning many Chriſtian Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; he tells them in the exerciſe of them, <hi>they ſhould keep the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Spirit in the Bond of Peace</hi> [<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: this Unity, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all diverſities is the ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>work of all Uniformity among Chriſtians] <hi>There is one Body, one
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:31515:70"/> Spirit, even as ye are called in one hope of your calling, &amp;c.</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable is <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. from the 13th verſe to the end, where he tells us, that Chriſt <hi>having aboliſhed in his Fleſh all enmity</hi> [between God and us, and between Jews and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles] <hi>thoſe that were a far off, are made nigh; he hath made in himſelf</hi> [being the common Head] <hi>of twain</hi> [i. e. Jew and Gentile] <hi>one new man</hi> [i. e. Chriſt Myſtical] <hi>ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Peace, &amp;c.</hi> ſee verſe 17. and ver. 18. <hi>For through him we both</hi> [Jews and Gentiles] <hi>have acceſs by one Spirit unto the Father;</hi> and then he goes on to tell them, that <hi>they are no more Strangers, &amp;c.</hi> but made a Spiritual Building upon the beſt Foundation, <hi>fitly framed toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, growing up into an holy Temple in the Lord, in whom alſo ye are builded together</hi> [i. e. the whole Catholick Body] <hi>for a habitation of God through the Spirit,</hi> which is
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:31515:71"/> the great Cement of this Spiritual Building that unites all the parts together, and every particular part to the Head.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The eminent uniting Graces which are wrought by the Spirit, is Faith and Love; Faith to our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and Love to one another. Love indeed is the moſt extenſive Union-Grace, becauſe it reacheth the whole Myſtical Body, both the Church Militant and Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant; Faith is an Eminent Grace of unſpeakable uſe to Saints, but it's only for their Militant State, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. But by Love both Saints Militant and Triumphant <hi>dwell in God, and God in them;</hi> 1 John 4.7, 16. <hi>And hereby we know that we dwell in him, and he in us; becauſe he hath given us of his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> verſe 13. But whilſt we are here, Faith muſt be <hi>primum movens,</hi> as to our Love; we muſt ſee him ſome way or other that we love;
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:31515:71"/> nay, we muſt be made nigh, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled in our minds, and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace him; and this cloſing, yea, firſt taſting of Chriſt, is by Faith; hence the Goſpel Miniſtry and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration, Eph. 4.12. <hi>is for the building up the Body of Chriſt</hi> fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and further, till all that do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to him do come, <hi>verſe</hi> 13. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, to the one-neſs of Faith, or full agreement in the Faith of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, <hi>to the knowledge of the Son of God</hi> [the Head] <hi>to a perfect man,</hi> [i. e. to make up the perfection of the Myſtical Manhood of Chriſt, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks elſewhere <hi>of filling up in his Body the Sufferings of Christ that remain;</hi> the calling in the Elect, is the perfecting the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Body of Chriſt] <hi>that hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth ye be no more Children, &amp;c.</hi> But <hi>ſpeaking the Truth in love;</hi> [<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, truthing it away in love, or walking ſincerely in love] <hi>doth grow up towards him, or upon
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:31515:72"/> him in all things, who is the Head even Chriſt;</hi> verſe 16. <hi>From whom [i. e.</hi> from the indwelling of whoſe Spirit] <hi>the whole Body is fitly articu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated, conjoyned and compacted toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> [ſo the words ſignify] <hi>by the ſupply of every Member</hi> [receiving of the diſtributions of the Spirit for the particular Shape, Uſe, Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and Office of each part deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined] <hi>according to the effectual working,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, according to the Energy or in-operation (<hi>viz.</hi> of the Spirit) in every part. We have alſo here <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and the ſame word <hi>Philip.</hi> 1.19. <hi>This ſhall turn to my Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, by the influence or ſupply of the Spirit, this influential ſupply is the cauſe of that excellency and beauty that appears in every part for the good of the whole.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Having proved the Spirit of Chriſt to be the common <hi>Nexus</hi> or Bond of Union in the Myſtical Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:31515:72"/> or Catholick Church; it is not hard to evince a bond of Union alſo in every particular Church: As the <hi>totum</hi> contains all the parts, and the parts make up the whole; So the Catholick Church contains all particular Churches, and the ſame Bond that tyes the whole together, tyes and limits each part; but as the Catholick Church is yet Myſtical, and not Viſible; becauſe its Bond of Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is ſuch; ſo when ever any part of this Church becomes viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, there muſt be a manifeſtation and diſcovery as much (as is poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) of this Bond of the Spirit, working by Faith and Love.</p>
               <p n="7">7. For conveniency of edificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Chriſt hath inſtituted ſeveral Congregations or Apartments in his Church, with a power of choo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing their own Officers, and enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all Ordinances according to Chriſts Will and Appointment.</p>
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:31515:73"/>
               <p>Theſe particular Congregations muſt each of them, as they are parts of the Catholick, have a manifeſtation of the Bond of the Spirit uniting them to Chriſt and to his Body; which manifeſtation, is the viſible form of a particular Church, and Church Memberſhip.</p>
               <p n="8">8. This manifeſtation, if it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed ſo far as to be a Bond of Union in a particular Spiritual Body Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick; it muſt be, firſt, A probable Profeſſion of this inward Bond of the Spirit working by Faith and Love, that the perſon or perſons ſo profeſſing may rationally, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Rules of Charity be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed of the number of the Faithful; which Profeſſing Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Ones are the only matter of a Particular Church of Chriſt; this is doing as Chriſtians, in the ſame manner as <hi>Paul</hi> did as a Miniſter, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.2. <hi>Renouncing the hidden
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:31515:73"/> things of darkneſs,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>by mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>festation of the Truth commending our ſelves to every mans Conſcience, in the ſight of God;</hi> but of this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>viz.</hi> That the true matter of a Particular Viſible Church, is viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Saints. 2. There muſt be ſomething or other to determine a man a Member of this or that Congregation, more then ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; all men that ſpeak of Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, ſay ſo: As ſome ſay Baptiſm, ſome ſay Cohabitation, and that Baptiſm only unites him to the Catholick Church, but Cohabita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion determines him to this or that particular. But we ſay it muſt be a voluntary and free ſubmiſſion of a mans ſelf to this or that So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety of Chriſts Flock, and the Diſcipline thereof, that can give him, or be to him the form of Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Church Memberſhip; it's not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ational or natural, that any man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hould be a Member, or be capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:31515:74"/> to claim the priviledges of any Society in the world, of what na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſoever it be, without his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. It's therefore a free volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary conſent and agreement, which is the true and proper external form of a particular Church, or Church-Memberſhip. Profeſſion is a viſible qualification of the matter, but it's conſent and agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which is the <hi>Copula</hi> or <hi>Nexus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For I challenge any man to give me one inſtance where Chriſt or his Apoſtles ever attempted to force any man to hear the Word, much leſs to believe it when they heard it, or to be of this or that Church. Beſides, it's a natural freedom to every man to chooſe what Government he will put himſelf under, as to his temporal Concerns; though when he hath done it, he be bound by the Laws thereof: much more a Chriſtian Liberty in reſpect of Spiritual Re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>giment.
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:31515:74"/> 3. God deſires nor ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of any forced Service, but requires the greateſt freedom and voluntary reſignation of themſelves in this kind. 4. I ſhall make it e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident, that all the Primitive Churches were ſo gathered: For the Apoſtles had no external force in any place of the Earth; <hi>it was not by power or might,</hi> i. e. humane, <hi>but by the Spirit of God;</hi> which wrought with the Word Preached, whereby their hearts were brought with freeneſs to embrace it, and with boldneſs to profeſs and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice it in the midſt of all oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and accordingly with the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt chearfulneſs and alacrity to conſent to a ſubjection to Chriſt, and all his Precepts and Inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in his Church. See in the firſt moſt Apoſtolical Church, the 120 that Chriſt left together at his Aſcention, Acts 1.14. <hi>And all theſe continued</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> &amp;c. <hi>with one
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:31515:75"/> conſent, unanimouſly in Prayer,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Chap.</hi> 2.41. <hi>And as many as received the Word</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>chearfully</hi> or <hi>gladly,</hi> yielded and ſubmitted to the Truth Preached and adviſed by <hi>Peter, theſe were baptized and added to the Church by the Apoſtles Doctrine, and in Fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip;</hi> which they would not have done, if they had not freely and upon choice and profeſſion embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced it. The firſt Church of the Gentiles that was gathered, was at <hi>Antioch.</hi> See how they came to be a Church, Acts 11.19, 20. <hi>And they that were ſcattered upon the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution that aroſe about</hi> Steven, <hi>Travelled ſo far as</hi> Phenice, &amp;c. verſe 20. <hi>And ſome of them were men of</hi> Cyprus <hi>and</hi> Cyrene, <hi>which when they were come to</hi> Antioch, <hi>ſpake unto the</hi> Grecians, <hi>Preaching the Lord Jeſus,</hi> verſe 21. <hi>And the hand of the Lord was with them;</hi> [The Spirit and Power of Chriſt] <hi>and a great number beleived</hi> [i. e.
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:31515:75"/> freely embraced the Truth] <hi>and turned unto the Lord.</hi> Now when <hi>Barnabas</hi> was ſent from <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to aid and encourage this great work, verſe 23. <hi>When he came and had ſeen the Grace of God, he was glad, and exhorted them all, that with pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of heart they would cleave unto the Lord;</hi> that is, that they would freely, voluntarily and ſincerely, without any hypocriſy, ſubmit themſelves to Chriſt and his Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, with manifeſtation of the fulleſt aſſent, and freeſt conſent that might be; now you find, verſ. 26. that they were immediately a Church upon this cleaving to the Lord, with whom <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas</hi> aſſembled, Preaching unto much people that attended their Miniſtry beſides, which were not yet of that gathered Church. I need not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large on this Point any further, the aſſertion being not only moſt agreeable to the beſt reaſon, but
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:31515:76"/> it being ſo clear, that this was the only way of Gathering Churches, uſed by the Apoſtles, and all their Coadjutors in the times of the Primitive Purity: If any hath practiced otherwiſe ſince, we are not obliged to be of their minds, or follow their examples; Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions of the Church proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from Antichriſt, and not from Chriſt.</p>
               <p>This is the day wherein the Lord is <hi>waſhing away the Filth of the Daughters of</hi> Zion [The Churches of Chriſt] <hi>and is purging away the Blood</hi> [The Antichriſtian Pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Worſhip] <hi>of Jeruſalem, from the midst of her, by the Spirit of Judgment, and Spirit of burning, Iſa.</hi> 4.4.</p>
               <p>And all the ſeven women that have laid hold on the Skirt of Chriſt, and called themſelves by
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:31515:76"/> his name, ſhall appear to be Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots; yea, as for thee O <hi>Aholibah,</hi> thus ſaith the Lord, <hi>Thou haſt walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the way of thy Siſter, therefore I will give her Cup into thy hand; thou ſhalt drink of thy Siſters Cup deep and large, thou ſhalt be laughed to ſcorn, and had in deriſion,</hi> Ezek. 23.31, 32. It containeth much.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="136" facs="tcp:31515:77"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> Of Church-Communion.</head>
               <p n="1">1. UNion according to its Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, Phyſical or Politick, or Oecumenical, naturally produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth a Communion ſuitable there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to; that which we are about to ſpeak of, is of a Spiritual, at leaſt of an Eccleſiaſtical Nature; we have ſhewn what is the primary Bond of Union in the Church of Chriſt, that it is the Spirit of Chriſt that animates, knits and tyes his whole Body together, and that this is Myſtical: But exerting it ſelf in vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal motions and operations in all the Members, it produceth a ſecond Bond, proper and neceſſary to the eſtabliſhment of a particular Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Church, which is a manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:31515:77"/> of this Spirit in a credible Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, and free conſent to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment and Ordinances of Chriſt, with a reſignation of our ſelves thereto; and this becomes the Bond of Church-Fellowſhip, and the Foundation of an orderly Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion.</p>
               <p>Communion is participation in one common benefit, or its mutual Participation or Communication of good things by various ſubjects.</p>
               <p>So Spiritual Communion is firſt a common participation in one general good or benefit of a Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Nature; and here where all the Members of Chriſt's Body partake of the ſame Head, the ſame Spirit, as their Unity conſiſts in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of connexion of Parts, ſo their Communion conſiſts in it in reſpect of Participation; and this <hi>is the Communion of the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> 2 Cor. 13.14. Its fully expreſſed as a Myſtical Communion, 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:31515:78"/> 3. <hi>That which we have ſeen and heard, declare we unto you, that you may have Fellowſhip with us; and truly our Fellowſhip is with the Father, and with his Son Jeſus Christ;</hi> This Communion in the Spirit is ſet forth unto us at large in that fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned place, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.4, 5, 6, 7, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> where he ſhews, that all the Graces, Gifts, Members, Operations, Offices in the Body, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their ſeveral diverſifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, flow from the ſame Spirit, all the ſtreams take indifferently from the ſame Fountain.</p>
               <p>This Communion in the Holy Ghoſt runs through the whole Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church in all Ages and Countries; for where the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Bond of Union is, this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion muſt be.</p>
               <p n="3">3. To make Communion in the Body compleat, there muſt not only be this Participation in a common good by all the Members,
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:31515:78"/> but a Communication of all good to each other mutually, as they are capable, and fellow-feeling with each other in all Sufferings.</p>
               <p>The Spirit of Chriſt thus influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encing all the Members, appears and manifeſts it ſelf in Graces and Gifts, variouſly working towards this mutual fellowſhip of Parts, both in good and evil of each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which are called the Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Spirit; as for Graces, the Principal wherein the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Communion doth conſiſt, are Faith and Love; and by theſe they Communicate with Chriſt the Head, receiving from him, and making return to him, as it were in a reciprocation, as alſo a mutual communication to, and with each other; for Faith is the leading Grace of Communion for our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſtate, by it we receive of the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Chriſt for Juſtification and Sanctification, <hi>John</hi> 1. and by Faith
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:31515:79"/> the Saints have communion one with another; for as it is the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the love of God in the heart, ſo it is of our love to our Brethren, believing them to be Juſtified in Chriſt Jeſus, and Members of his Body: for Love founded on the Faith of the good eſtate of another, is properly Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; the credibility of anothers Profeſſion, gives ground of Faith, that he is what he profeſſeth; and this joyned with Love, makes Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; wherefore the Apoſtle takes it in this ſence, when he ſaith, <hi>Phile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> 5. <hi>Hearing of thy Love and Faith which thou hast toward our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and all Saints:</hi> Moreover by Faith the Saints viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble have a kind of Communion, with thoſe that went before, and who are to come after; it being the ſubſtance of things [or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in futurition] hoped for, and the evidence [or demonſtration of
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:31515:79"/> the Truth] of things not ſeen, [<hi>i. e.</hi> removed from ſence, by timen parterition, or place in abſence;] ſo thereby we ſee the Saints and thoſe Truths atteſted by them in Ages paſt.</p>
               <p n="4">4. As for Love, it's not only the moſt eminent Grace of actual com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion between Chriſt and his Members, and of them with each other in the ſtate that we are in here; but it's almoſt the only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining when we go hence, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.13. <hi>John</hi> treats much of the tranſcendent excellency of this Grace throughout his Epiſtle, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.11. <hi>If God ſo loved us, we ought to love one another,</hi> 12. <hi>If we love one another, God dwelleth in us, and his love is made perfect in us:</hi> by this Grace we have communion with all Saints Militant and Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.1. <hi>Every one that loveth him that is begot, loveth him that is begotten of him.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="142" facs="tcp:31515:80"/>
               <p n="5">5. Now by Communion in theſe two Graces, the Church grows up to its full perfection; the Apoſtle ſaying, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.12. <hi>That the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry and Miniſtration is for the Building up of the Body of Chriſt,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> [agreement in all points of Faith, and Profeſſion of it] <hi>and to the knowledge of the Son of God,</hi> [the Head] <hi>to the perfect man, to the meaſure of the Stature of the fullneſs of Christ</hi> [Myſtical] filling up his Body, and receiving influen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially of his Fulneſs by Faith, and v. 15. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, do grow more and more ſincere in Love; this Love ſhews it ſelf in its fellow-feeling, alſo that it works in us, whereby we communicate in each others Sufferings, and ſupply each others wants, for the good of the whole; this part of Communion is fully diſcourſed by the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.13, 14, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yea in the moſt part of the Chapter.</p>
               <pb n="143" facs="tcp:31515:80"/>
               <p n="6">6. Thus far Communion belongs to the Church under its Catholick conſideration in its Myſtical State; there muſt be ſome external actions and things that are viſible, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the Communion of theſe Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces muſt be manifeſt, in Miniſtry, Offices, Gifts, Ordinances, but all for and from the Spirit, and theſe eminent Graces of Faith and Love.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Communion then of particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Congregations muſt be by Chriſt's Ordination viſible in thoſe ſacred Means and Ordinances ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by Chriſt for its growth, confirmation, and building up in Grace and Truth. God having made his Church in its viſible ſtate, the Nurſery of Grace, and the Knowledge of the Truth, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.12. <hi>For the perfecting of the Saints, for the work of the Miniſtry, for the edifying the Body of Christ, [i. e.</hi> in the militanting viſible part] 13. <hi>till we all come in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:31515:81"/> Faith, and the Knowledge of the Son of God, unto a perfect man, unto the meaſure of the ſtature of the full<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Christ.</hi> Verſe 14. <hi>That we ſhould be henceforth no more Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. The Edification of the Church being appointed by Chriſt in a way of Communion; we are to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, 1. wherein this viſible commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion doth conſiſt; 2. what is the ground and end of it: 3. where, and between whom it is. 1. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in doth it conſiſt? It doth conſiſt, firſt in participation of ſome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon benefit and advantages, which a particular Congregation are ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of, and have frequent fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip together in, and theſe are Church-Gifts and Church-Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.42. <hi>They continued ſtedfaſt in the Apoſtles Doctrine and Fellowſhip, in Breaking Bread and in Prayers;</hi> and for this end hath <hi>Chriſt</hi> furniſhed his Church with
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:31515:81"/> Miniſtry and Ordinances, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. Miniſtry by erecting extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and ordinary for the planting of his Church; our Saviour thought meet to ſend them with extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Commiſſion and qualificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons thoſe that were ſuch, were eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially <hi>Apostles, Prophets,</hi> &amp; <hi>Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts,</hi> 1 Cor. 12.28. <hi>First Apostles, ſecondarily Prophets,</hi> Eph. 4.11. Theſe were all to be Witneſſes of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection and Aſcenſion of our Lord Jeſus, and confirm their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine by Miracles, had their inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Holy Ghoſt, ſpecial Preſence of God, and power in the Churches wherever they came, eſpecially the Apoſtles.</p>
               <p n="9">9. The Apoſtles were XII, which waited upon our Lord during his Miniſtry on earth, before his Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings; <hi>Judas</hi> then falling from his Miniſtry, when our Lord Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended he left eleven, to which <hi>Matthias</hi> was added by Lot, and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:31515:82"/> of the Church, <hi>Act.</hi> 1. to theſe two more were added after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, by ſpecial command of the Holy Ghoſt to the Prophets in the Church at <hi>Antioch,</hi> Act. 13.1, 2, 3. compared with <hi>chap.</hi> 14.14. <hi>Which when the Apoſtles Barnabas and Paul heard of;</hi> and before that Ordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Barnabas</hi> was but a Prophet, ſent from the Church at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to aſſiſt them that were there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; as appears <hi>chap.</hi> 11.22, 23. and <hi>chap.</hi> 13.1.</p>
               <p n="10">10. The Prophets, I apprehend to be ſuch, who were furniſhed with Gifts and Graces, and extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry inſpiration; their Call and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion being ſuch, for the calling of the Gentiles, and gathering the Churches: And I ſuppoſe them to be thoſe Brethren of the 120 that waited together at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> till they were baptized with the Holy Ghoſt and fire, being all equally with the Apoſtles furniſhed with
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:31515:82"/> the gift of Tongues (though ſecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dary to them in their power) for the diſpenſing the Goſpel to all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and therefore upon the ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering the Church of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Stephens</hi> Perſecution; theſe Prophets moſtly began the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of the Gentiles by their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry at firſt: My Reaſons for it are, 1. That its evident all the Brethren as well as the Apoſtles were extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinarily furniſhed for the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, Act. 2.4. <hi>They were all filled with the Holy Ghost, and began to ſpeak with other tongues, &amp;c.</hi> Now this was for ſpecial ends, that they were capacitated to ſpeak to all Nations in their own Languages.</p>
               <p n="2">2. We find upon <hi>Stevens Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Act.</hi> 8.1. that they were all ſcattered, except the Apoſtles; not the whole Church, for we read of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of that Church ſtill, but all the Brethren of the 120 were ſcattered throughout the Regions of <hi>Judea</hi> &amp; <hi>Samaria,</hi> by whole means Churches
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:31515:83"/> of the <hi>Jews</hi> were gathered, as it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, verſe 14. and <hi>Acts</hi> 9.31. After God had taken off that great Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer <hi>Saul,</hi> then had all the Churches <hi>rest throughout all Judea, Galilee and Samaria.</hi> Likewiſe we find that the Church of <hi>Antioch,</hi> the firſt among the <hi>Gentiles</hi> that we read of, was Planted by their Miniſtry; ſee <hi>Acts</hi> 11.19, 20, 22. compare with <hi>ch.</hi> 13. 1. More might be ſaid on this point but <hi>I</hi> muſt keep to the preſent de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, only naming the ſeveral Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
               <p n="11">11 The third kind of extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dary Officers, were <hi>Evangeliſts,</hi> ſuch as <hi>Steven, Phillip, Luke, Mark, Timothy, &amp;c.</hi> they were men no doubt extraordinarily qualified, and were called Evangeliſts, as being Aſſiſtants to the Apoſtles, and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velled with them, and ſometimes alone, as <hi>Philip:</hi> It may be doubted whether the ſeven Deacons were of that 120 Brethren, for they were
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:31515:83"/> men full of the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>ch.</hi> 6. 3. and afterward being pitched up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for eminent Service to the <hi>Church,</hi> were called now Evangeliſts; but being not of the number that were together at our Saviours Aſcenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Pentecoſt, and though their work might be the ſame with the Prophets, yet their dignity was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour to the Apoſtles and Prophets, as <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. <hi>Some Apoſtles, ſome Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, ſome Evangeliſts;</hi> but we need not lay much ſtreſs now upon the differences of thoſe Offices cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; thoſe Officers, eſpecially Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and Prophets, are irrecovera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly ceaſed from the very nature of them; for an Apoſtle, it were requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to be one who had ſeen the Lord, and a Prophet (according to what we endeavour to prove) one of thoſe that <hi>were baptized with the Ghoſt and Fire at Pentecoſt.</hi> As for an Evangeliſt, it's moſt proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to remain, if any, becauſe the
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:31515:84"/> work ſtill remains neceſſary to the encreaſe of the Church, <hi>viz.</hi> Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching to Unconverted people, and gathering of Churches; tho' none can be expected ſince the Primitive Times with any more then ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry qualifications which any ſtated Church-officer hath, ſuch Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts &amp; ſuch Deacons cannot be had: But to ſupply thoſe Offices neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary now in the Church, thoſe that are to be mentioned are ſufficient.</p>
               <p n="12">12. The Ordinary Officers re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining in the Church now, may be reduced to theſe two heads, <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and Deacons;</hi> Elders, for Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry and Government; Deacons, to ſerve Tables, to look after the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary charges for the Miniſtry, Ordinances, Aſſemblies, Poor, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I ſhall not enlarge here, it being e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident to every one acquainted with Scripture.</p>
               <p n="13">13. The Ordinances of Ordinary Communion, are Prayer, Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:31515:84"/> the Word, Sacraments, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. Collections. The Lords Supper is ſtill ſpoken of as the moſt eminent Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Communion, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16.</p>
               <p n="14">14. If we enquire for the ground and end of Communion in theſe Ordinances, it is, That this is the way appointed by Chriſt for the edifying his Body, for the encreaſe of Faith and Love in the Members of Chriſt; thoſe Ordinances being deſigned indeed, as to the Church, for edification; for its not to be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed that a Church-Member ſhould be an unconverted perſon; if a hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite creep in, he hath nothing of true end and deſign of Communion. So that by Communion the Body of Chriſt is nouriſhed, ſtrengthened and perfected, towards <hi>its fullneſs of ſtature in Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="15">15. If it be enquired where Church Communion is, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween what kind of perſons? I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, Church Communion in Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances,
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:31515:85"/> can be but in one particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Congregation, at the ſame time, where all may meet for edification in one place, &amp; we read of no other in the Primitive Church; tho ſome would have that of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to be greater then ſo, after the addition of 3000; but its expreſly ſaid, that they <hi>were all together in Fellowſhip,</hi> and met together ſtill before the diſperſion, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.42.44. alſo <hi>chap.</hi> 5.12. and other places; but this great Church was ſcattered after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards by Gods Providence, order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it for the great advantage of the Goſpel, and propagation of Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</p>
               <p n="16">16. If it be inquired between whom Church-Communion is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed? The anſwer is eaſy, It's between particular Members, that ordinarily have fellowſhip in the ſame particular Congregations; as likewiſe between one particular Church and another, all Churches
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:31515:85"/> comunicating in this, that they are of the ſame univerſal Body, have the ſame Head, Bond of Union, Graces, Ordinances, Priviledges, as in the one intire Catholick Body; as every individual perſon in fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is a Member in particular, ſo every individual Church is a part of that <hi>Integrum</hi> compacted by that vvhich every joynt ſupplyeth,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.16.</note> according to the effectual working in the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of every part, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="17">17. Communion we have ſaid, as it ſtands in copartnerſhip in ſome common good, ſo in communicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on between Member and Member; what of peculiar good is in any part, is communicable to the reſt, or fellow-feeling of the Sufferings of each other. As there is a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon deſign carri'd on by every part for the good of the whole, ſo by all parts for each other: The Apoſtle tells us this at large, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.</p>
               <pb n="154" facs="tcp:31515:86"/>
               <p n="18">18. The mutual communication that is viſible in order to ſpiritual advantage, ſtands in giving and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving by the exerciſe of ſpiritual gifts and graces in the Word and Prayer, by mutual advice and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, by admonition and Church-cenſures, where required; by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributions to the wants and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities of each other any way ariſing, <hi>Spiritual or Temporal.</hi> This Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion is practicable between <hi>Church</hi> and Church alſo, not only by occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſional participation in the Word and Ordinances with each other, but in the matters before mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of advice and ſupply of each others wants: In the former caſe, we have the example of the Church of <hi>Antioch,</hi> adviſing with the Church of <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> in the latter, that 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.5. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.3, 4. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.6. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb n="155" facs="tcp:31515:86"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XI.</hi> The Concluſion.</head>
               <p>BEing not minded to enlarge this diſcourſe any further at this time, I ſhall only lay down a few Corolary Aſſertions briefly to obviate ſome objections that may riſe in ſome mens minds againſt what hath been ſpoken, which we ſhall be ready to defend, if occaſion requires.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That that only is a true conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted Church of Chriſt, which is a houſe of Gods Building; it's not mans fancy or pretentions, that renders any thing ſo.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That a Chriſtians actual Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with any one true Viſible
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:31515:87"/> Church of Chriſt, makes him a Member in Communion with all the Churches of Chriſt; though he doth not at preſent, nor hath occaſion to communicate with any Congregated Body, beſides what he is actually and immediately in Communion with.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Hence barely Non-Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion as to immediate Participation in Ordinances with this or that Church, doth not Unchurch them, (as ſome men phraſe it) <hi>i. e.</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn their ſtanding, neither is it any part of Schiſm or cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable Separation.</p>
               <p n="4">4. There is a Separation that is abſolutely neceſſary to every True Viſible Church of Chriſt, there can be none without it, and it is the duty of True Churches and Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers to practice it.</p>
               <p n="5">5. This Separation is from the World, Fleſh and Devil, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore from all the children of theſe,
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:31515:87"/> and from all falſe Churches what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever.</p>
               <p n="6">6. That all Antichriſtian Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, as well as abſolutely Heathen, are Idol-temples, and therefore Communion with them is fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with <hi>Belial</hi> and his Idols, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.</p>
               <p n="7">7. That Chriſt hath had his true Worſhippers and Churches during the whole time of the Antichriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Reign and Rage, but in a Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs, eſpecially as to Viſible Form and Conſtitution; yea trod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den down by the Gentiles for the moſt part; preſerved notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by Chriſt in ſome times and places in its eſſential myſtical ſtate, at leaſt without any viſible luſtre in Externals, as the Church of Old in <hi>Egypt</hi> and <hi>Babylon;</hi> in other times and places he hath ſecured them in ſome retirements, ſo far as to have opportunity to erect <hi>Tabernacles</hi> of true Goſpel conſtitutions in
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:31515:88"/> form and faſhion as he primitively appointed.</p>
               <p n="8">8. And thus the true Churches of Chriſt hath ſtood during the time of the Womans militating in the Wilderneſs, under its ſeveral Scatterings, Deformations and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formations, under which God hath owned them all the dayes of their wanderings in the Wilderneſs.</p>
               <p n="9">9. God hath had his degrees of Reformation and Purity of his Church, eſpecially during the laſt part of the Beaſts Reign, and that all ſuch degrees have been progreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in Separation, as to Purity of Ordinances and Worſhip, till at laſt there ſhall be a perfect full and clear Redemption of <hi>Zion</hi> from all her Captivity in this Spiritual <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt and Babylon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">10. Schiſm is a thing talked more of then underſtood; we only affirm this concerning it, 1. That Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration from a manifeſtly falſe
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:31515:88"/> Church is no Schiſm. 2. Non-com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with a ſuſpected Church, is no Schiſm, but a duty. 3. That all Schiſm ſpoken of in Scripture, is actually and immediately in ſome particular Congregation, being a Viſible Politick Body; and thoſe there mentioned are not all ampu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, or rentings aſunder; moſt of them are but diviſions in ſome matters of judgment and affection, without a deſtruction of the whole as in the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> though there may be ſome tendency there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto.</p>
               <p n="11">11. Manifeſt Corruptions in Worſhip perſiſted in, eſpecially if ſuch as are taken up again, after they have been abundantly wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed againſt, and purged out by former degrees of Reformation, are to be ſeparated from, and wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed againſt, and ſuch Churches as maintain them: Yea, ſuch Separation is ſo far from a juſt
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:31515:89"/> charge of Schiſm, that it is a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Duty of all thoſe whoſe Minds and Conſciences are infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in the truth of the Goſpel.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:31515:89"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
